[
  {
    "questionNum": 83001,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിലെ ഏറ്റവും വലിയ വാർത്താ ഏജൻസി ഏതാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " പ്രസ് ട്രസ്റ്റ് ഒഫ് ഇന്ത്യ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83002,
    "questionText": " പ്രസാർ ഭാരതി സ്ഥാപിതമായ വർഷമേത്? ",
    "answerText": " 1997 നവംബർ 23 "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83003,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിലെ റേഡിയോ സംപ്രേഷണം ഓൾ ഇന്ത്യ റേഡിയോ എന്നു നാമകരണം ചെയ്ത വർഷമേത്? ",
    "answerText": 1936
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83004,
    "questionText": " ദൂരദർശൻ ദിവസേനയുള്ള സംപ്രേഷണം തുടങ്ങിയ വർഷമേത്? ",
    "answerText": 1965
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83005,
    "questionText": " Where is the head office of New India Assurance?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83006,
    "questionText": " ദൂരദർശന്റെ ആപ്തവാക്യം എന്താണ്? ",
    "answerText": " സത്യം ശിവം സുന്ദരം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83007,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിൽ കളർ ടിവി സംപ്രേഷണം തുടങ്ങിയ വർഷമേത്? ",
    "answerText": 1982
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83008,
    "questionText": " The celebrated work on Indian economic history ‘The Industrial Evolution in India in Recent Times’ was written by?",
    "answerText": " D.R.Gadgil"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83009,
    "questionText": " അന്റാർട്ടിക്കയിലെ ഇന്ത്യയുടെ മൂന്നാമത്തെ പര്യവേക്ഷണകേന്ദ്രം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഭാരതി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83010,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയുടെ പ്രഥമ ആർട്ടിക്ക് പര്യവേക്ഷണ സംഘത്തെ നയിച്ചതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " രസിക്ക് രവീന്ദ്ര "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83011,
    "questionText": " The apex bank of industrial credit in India?",
    "answerText": " IDBI"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83012,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യൻ ആണവ ഗവേഷണത്തിന്റെ പിതാവ് എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഹോമി ജഹാംഗീർ ഭാഭ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83013,
    "questionText": " The first National Income Committee was constituted in the year?",
    "answerText": 1949
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83014,
    "questionText": " The full form of ‘P.P.P.’ in financial world?",
    "answerText": " Purchasing Power Parity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83015,
    "questionText": " ഏഷ്യയിലെ തന്നെ ആദ്യത്തെ ആണവ ഗവേഷണ റിയാക്ടറേത്? ",
    "answerText": " അപ്സര "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83016,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയുടെ ആദ്യത്തെ ആണവ പരീക്ഷണത്തിന്റെ രഹസ്യനാമം എന്തായിരുന്നു? ",
    "answerText": " ബുദ്ധൻ ചിരിക്കുന്നു "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83017,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യൻ അണുബോംബിന്റെ പിതാവ് എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോ. രാജാരാമണ്ണ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83018,
    "questionText": " The prominent function of Central Statistical Organisation?",
    "answerText": " To collect national income statistics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83019,
    "questionText": " കൂടംകുളം ആണവ വൈദ്യുത നിലയം തമിഴ്‌നാട്ടിലെ ഏത് ജില്ലയിലാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " തിരുനെൽവേലി ജില്ല "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83020,
    "questionText": " കക്രപ്പാർ ആണവ നിലയം ഏതു സംസ്ഥാനത്താണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ഗുജറാത്തിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83021,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യൻ സൂപ്പർ കമ്പ്യൂട്ടറിന്റെ പിതാവ് എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോ. വിജയ് പി. ഭട്‌കർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83022,
    "questionText": " 1896ൽ ഇന്ത്യയിൽ ആദ്യമായി സിനിമ പ്രദർശിപ്പിച്ചത് എവിടെയാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " മുംബയ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83023,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of Allahabad bank is in?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83024,
    "questionText": " The economic planning proposed by eight leading industrialists in 1945 is known as?",
    "answerText": " Bombay plan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83025,
    "questionText": " The insurance company that was founded by Dorab Tata?",
    "answerText": " New India Assurance"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83026,
    "questionText": " NAFED is connected with?",
    "answerText": " Agricultural marketing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83027,
    "questionText": " The identifying number given to the income tax payers by the Department is?",
    "answerText": " Permanent Account Number"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83028,
    "questionText": " Which five year plan was called Harrold Domer model?",
    "answerText": " First FYP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83029,
    "questionText": " A multinational is?",
    "answerText": " A company operating in many countries"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83030,
    "questionText": " Economic growth is usually coupled with?",
    "answerText": " Inflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83031,
    "questionText": " In which country Green Revolution was started?",
    "answerText": " Mexico"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83032,
    "questionText": " National Development Council was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83033,
    "questionText": " The ex officio chairman of the National Development Council is?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83034,
    "questionText": " The first book on Indian Planning entitled ‘Planned Economy’ for India was the attempt of?",
    "answerText": " M.Visvesvarayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83035,
    "questionText": " The first Insurance company established for Indians?",
    "answerText": " Bombay Mutual Life Assurance Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83036,
    "questionText": " The Panchayat Raj system was introduced in 1959 under the recommendation of?",
    "answerText": " Belwant Rai Mehta Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83037,
    "questionText": " Repo rate means?",
    "answerText": " The rate at which RBI sells securities in Commercial Bank"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83038,
    "questionText": " Father of Green Revolution in India?",
    "answerText": " M.S.Swaminathan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83039,
    "questionText": " In which area priority was given in the first Five year Plan?",
    "answerText": " Agriculture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83040,
    "questionText": " In which field Co-operative Movement was started for the first time in India?",
    "answerText": " Agricultural Credit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83041,
    "questionText": " When was the New Liberalized Industrial Policy was announced in India?",
    "answerText": 1991
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83042,
    "questionText": " The main objective of Prime Minister’s Grama Sadak Yojana(PMGSY)?",
    "answerText": " To construct all weather roads to connect hilly areas and main roads"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83043,
    "questionText": " People’s Plan was envisaged by?",
    "answerText": " M.N.Roy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83044,
    "questionText": " Which Five Year Plan is referred to as ‘Industrial and Transport Plan’?",
    "answerText": " Second"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83045,
    "questionText": " India copied the idea of Five Year Plans from?",
    "answerText": " Former Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83046,
    "questionText": " The Ashok Mehta Committee was appointed in?",
    "answerText": 1977
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83047,
    "questionText": " The Rolling Plan concept in National Planning was introduced by?",
    "answerText": " Janatha Government"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83048,
    "questionText": " Where is National Institute of Rural Development situated?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83049,
    "questionText": " Who is known as Father of Indian Budget?",
    "answerText": " P.C.Mahalanobis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83050,
    "questionText": " Who was the Prime Minister of India when Prime Minister’s Rozgar Yojana (PMRY) was started?",
    "answerText": " P.V.Narasimha Rao"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83051,
    "questionText": " Who gave the slogan “Garibi Hatao”(Eradicate Poverty)?",
    "answerText": " Indira Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83052,
    "questionText": " The Belwant Rai Mehta Committee was appointed by?",
    "answerText": " National Development Counci"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83053,
    "questionText": " Which body compiles the national income of India?",
    "answerText": " Central Statistical Organisation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83054,
    "questionText": " The first Five year Plan was started in?",
    "answerText": 1951
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83055,
    "questionText": " The major emphasis of Third Five Year Plan was?",
    "answerText": " Making India self-reliant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83056,
    "questionText": " During which Five Year Plan, the Twenty Point Programme (TPP) was launched by Indira Gandhi?",
    "answerText": " Fifth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83057,
    "questionText": " The first Asian country to start Community Development Project?",
    "answerText": " India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83058,
    "questionText": " What is functioned in Phiroze Jeejeebhoy Towers?",
    "answerText": " Bombay Stock Excahnge"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83059,
    "questionText": " The originator of Human Development Index?",
    "answerText": " Mahbub ul Haq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83060,
    "questionText": " The Indian capital market is under the control of?",
    "answerText": " SEBI"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83061,
    "questionText": " The acronym SEBI stands for?",
    "answerText": " Securities and Exchange Board of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83062,
    "questionText": " The monetary policy in India is formulated by?",
    "answerText": " Reserve Bank of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83063,
    "questionText": " The return on debentures is called?",
    "answerText": " Interest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83064,
    "questionText": " The south Indian city which is the hub of automobile industry?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83065,
    "questionText": " Which nation is considered to be the originator of the concept of micro finance?",
    "answerText": " Bangladesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83066,
    "questionText": " Bombay Mutual Life Assurance Society was founded in?",
    "answerText": 1870
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83067,
    "questionText": " Green Revolution in India is also known as?",
    "answerText": " Seed; fertilizer and irrigation revolution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83068,
    "questionText": " The first jute mill in India was established in 1854 at Rishra near....?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83069,
    "questionText": " The industry which laid the foundation of industrialisation in India?",
    "answerText": " Cotton textiles"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83070,
    "questionText": " The main competitor for Indian jute industry is?",
    "answerText": " Bangladesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83071,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the father of Indian industry?",
    "answerText": " Jamshedji Tata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83072,
    "questionText": " The second largest agriculture based industry in India?",
    "answerText": " Sugar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83073,
    "questionText": " The head office of United India Insurance Company Limited is at?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83074,
    "questionText": " In which year Oriental Insurance Company Ltd became a subsidiary of LIC?",
    "answerText": 1956
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83075,
    "questionText": " In which year New India Assurance company was founded?",
    "answerText": 1919
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83076,
    "questionText": " Oriental Life Insurance Company was started in?",
    "answerText": 1818
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83077,
    "questionText": " The first modern paper mill in India was established in Sehrampur in ....... in 1832?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83078,
    "questionText": " The first modern silk manufacturing unit was started in .......in 1832?",
    "answerText": " Howra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83079,
    "questionText": " Which is known as the Steel City of India?",
    "answerText": " Jamshedpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83080,
    "questionText": " Which city is known as Manchester of South India?",
    "answerText": " Coimbatore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83081,
    "questionText": " The largest producer of jute in India?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83082,
    "questionText": " The most important industry in India in terms of employment and production of export goods?",
    "answerText": " Cotton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83083,
    "questionText": " Which state is the largest producer of silk in India?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83084,
    "questionText": " Durgapur and Burnpur in West Bengal is famous for ..... industry?",
    "answerText": " Iron and Steel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83085,
    "questionText": " Bhadravati, famous for Iron and steel industry, is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83086,
    "questionText": " Mazagaon Dock limited is in?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83087,
    "questionText": " Garden Reach Shipbuilders limited is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83088,
    "questionText": " Where is Hindustan shipyard limited?",
    "answerText": " Visakhapatnam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83089,
    "questionText": " The first fertilizer factory in independent India in public sector?",
    "answerText": " Sindri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83090,
    "questionText": " Nepanagar is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Newsprint"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83091,
    "questionText": " Pimpri and Rishikesh are famous for ...... factories?",
    "answerText": " Antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83092,
    "questionText": " In which state is Salem steel factory?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83093,
    "questionText": " Ludhiana famous for cycles situated in?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83094,
    "questionText": " Sholapur famous for cotton textiles is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83095,
    "questionText": " Aligarh in Uttar Pradesh is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Locks"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83096,
    "questionText": " Which is called ‘Pittsburg of India’?",
    "answerText": " Jamshedpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83097,
    "questionText": " The place in Tamil Nadu famous for the manufacturing of battle tanks?",
    "answerText": " Avady"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83098,
    "questionText": " The first oil refinery in India?",
    "answerText": " Digboi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83099,
    "questionText": " Firozabad in Uttar Pradesh is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Glass bangles"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83100,
    "questionText": " Jallander in Punjab is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Sports goods"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83101,
    "questionText": " Ahmedabad in Gujarat is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Cotton mills"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83102,
    "questionText": " Dhariwal in Punjab is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Wool"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83103,
    "questionText": " Which place is called Detroit of India?",
    "answerText": " Pithampur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83104,
    "questionText": " Haldia in West Bengal is famous for?",
    "answerText": " Oil refinery"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83105,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Khetri mines in Rajastan is famous?",
    "answerText": " Copper"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83106,
    "questionText": " In which state is Singbhum mines famous for Iron and Copper?",
    "answerText": " Jharkhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83107,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Zawar mines in Rajastan is famous?",
    "answerText": " Zinc"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83108,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest producer of Asbestos in India?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83109,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Koraput (Orissa), Cudappah (Andhra Pradesh) and Salem (Tamil Nadu) are famous?",
    "answerText": " Aluminium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83110,
    "questionText": " Which mineral is known as ‘black gold’?",
    "answerText": " Petroleum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83111,
    "questionText": " In which state is Kolar, Hutti gold mines?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83112,
    "questionText": " In which state is Ramagiri gold mines?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83113,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Koderma mines are famous?",
    "answerText": " Mica"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83114,
    "questionText": " The largest source of petroleum in India?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai High"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83115,
    "questionText": " The variety of coal with the highest amount of carbon content?",
    "answerText": " Anthrasite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83116,
    "questionText": " What is known as ‘hard coal’?",
    "answerText": " Anthrasite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83117,
    "questionText": " What is known as ‘brown coal’?",
    "answerText": " Lignite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83118,
    "questionText": " The variety of coal used in India in largest extent?",
    "answerText": " Bitumin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83119,
    "questionText": " Which Indian state leads in the production of Anthrasite?",
    "answerText": " Jammu Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83120,
    "questionText": " Leading producer of Lignite in India?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83121,
    "questionText": " The plateau in India famous for mineral resources?",
    "answerText": " Chotanagpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83122,
    "questionText": " Which is known as Ruhr of India?",
    "answerText": " Chotanagpur Plateau"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83123,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Asansol in West Bengal, Sambalpur in Orissa, Jharia and Dhanbad in Jharkhand are famous?",
    "answerText": " Coal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83124,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Cambay in Gujarat is famous?",
    "answerText": " Petroleum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83125,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Jaduguda mines in Jharkhand is famous?",
    "answerText": " Uranium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83126,
    "questionText": " Which state is the leading producer of minerals in India which earned the nick name ‘the mineral state of India’?",
    "answerText": " Jharkhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83127,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Jhunjhunun, Kolihan,Sikar mines in Rajastan are famous?",
    "answerText": " Copper"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83128,
    "questionText": " For which mineral Panna in Madhya Pradesh is famous?",
    "answerText": " Diamond"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83129,
    "questionText": " In which state is Raniganj coal mines?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83130,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest source of energy in India?",
    "answerText": " Thermal power"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83131,
    "questionText": " The National Thermal Power Corporation was established in?",
    "answerText": 1975
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83132,
    "questionText": " The oldest nuclear power project in India?",
    "answerText": " Tarapur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83133,
    "questionText": " Indira Gandhi atomic power project, Kalpakkam is in?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83134,
    "questionText": " Rawatbhatta atomic power project is in?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83135,
    "questionText": " Narora atomic power project is in?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83136,
    "questionText": " Kaiga atomic power project is in?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83137,
    "questionText": " Nuclear power station in Gujarat is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Kakrapar\\"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83138,
    "questionText": " The Kudankulam atomic power project in Tirunelveli district of Tamil Nadu has been bulit in collaboration with?",
    "answerText": " Russia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83139,
    "questionText": " In which river is Nagarjuna Sagar dam is built?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83140,
    "questionText": " The Sardar Sarovar Project in Gujarat is in ......river?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83141,
    "questionText": " In which state is Nathpa Jhakri Hydroelectric Power Project?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83142,
    "questionText": " In which state is Koyna hydel project?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83143,
    "questionText": " In which river is Sivasamudram project in Karnataka?",
    "answerText": " Kaveri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83144,
    "questionText": " In which state are the Uri, Salal, Dulhasti hydel projects?",
    "answerText": " Jammu Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83145,
    "questionText": " Omkareswar hydel project is in?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83146,
    "questionText": " Machkund project is an inter state project of Odish and______?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83147,
    "questionText": " Which dam was described as ‘New Temple of Resurgent India’ by Jawahar Lal Nehru?",
    "answerText": " Bhakra dam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83148,
    "questionText": " Bhakra Dam is located in the village of Bhakra in the Bilaspur region of?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83149,
    "questionText": " In which state is Loktak Dam?",
    "answerText": " Manipur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83150,
    "questionText": " Balimela hydel project is a joint venture of Andhra Pradesh and ......?",
    "answerText": " Odisha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83151,
    "questionText": " Kalinadi hydel project is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83152,
    "questionText": " Mettur Dam in Tamil Nadu is in ..... river?",
    "answerText": " Kaveri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83153,
    "questionText": " In which river is Indira Sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83154,
    "questionText": " Govind Vallabh Pant Sagar dam is in?",
    "answerText": " Rihand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83155,
    "questionText": " Maharana Pratap Sagar dam (Pong dam) is in?",
    "answerText": " Beas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83156,
    "questionText": " In which river is Rana Pratap sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Chambal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83157,
    "questionText": " In which river is Nagarjuna Sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83158,
    "questionText": " In which river is Govind Sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Chambal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83159,
    "questionText": " In which river Jawahar Sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Chambal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83160,
    "questionText": " In which state is Krishnarajasagar dam in Kaveri?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83161,
    "questionText": " In which river is Alamatty Dam?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83162,
    "questionText": " In which river is Hiracud Dam in Odisha?",
    "answerText": " Mahanadi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83163,
    "questionText": " Nizam Sagar dam in Andhra Pradesh is in ...... river?",
    "answerText": " Manjira"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83164,
    "questionText": " In which river is Tawa Dam?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83165,
    "questionText": " In which river is Tehri Dam in Uttarakhand?",
    "answerText": " Bhagirathi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83166,
    "questionText": " In which river is Ukai project in Gujarat?",
    "answerText": " Tapti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83167,
    "questionText": " The first multi purpose project in independent India (1948)?",
    "answerText": " Damodar valley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83168,
    "questionText": " ഉപരാഷ്ട്രപതിയായശേഷം രാഷ്ട്രപതിയായ വ്യക്തി? ",
    "answerText": " കെ.ആർ. നാരായണൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83169,
    "questionText": " The highest dam in India?",
    "answerText": " Tehri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83170,
    "questionText": " തായ്‌ലൻഡ്, തുർക്കി, യു.എസ്.എ, ചൈന എന്നീ രാജ്യങ്ങളിലെ അംബാസഡർ, ജവഹർലാൽ നെഹ്‌റു യൂണിവേഴ്സിറ്റി വൈസ് ചാൻസലർ എന്നീ പദവികൾ വഹിച്ച ഇന്ത്യൻ പ്രസിഡന്റ്? ",
    "answerText": " കെ.ആർ. നാരായണൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83171,
    "questionText": " In which river is Bhakra Nangal dam?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83172,
    "questionText": " The reservoir of Bhakra dam is known as?",
    "answerText": " Govind sagar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83173,
    "questionText": " The Govind Sagar dam in Shahzad river is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83174,
    "questionText": " In which river is Gandhi sagar dam?",
    "answerText": " Chambal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83175,
    "questionText": " In which river is Baglihar project and Dulhasti project in Jammu Kashmir?",
    "answerText": " Chenab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83176,
    "questionText": " ദക്ഷിണേന്ത്യക്കാരനായ ആദ്യ രാഷ്ട്രപതി? ",
    "answerText": " എസ്. രാധാകൃഷ്ണൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83177,
    "questionText": " In which river is Osman Sagar Reservoir in Telengana?",
    "answerText": " Musi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83178,
    "questionText": " In which river is Linganamakki dam in Karnataka?",
    "answerText": " Sharavati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83179,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിൽ ആദ്യമായി അടിയന്തരവാസ്ഥ പ്രഖ്യാപിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോ. എസ്. രാധാകൃഷ്ണൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83180,
    "questionText": " In which river is Ranjeet Sagar Dam?",
    "answerText": " Beas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83181,
    "questionText": " മണ്ടേലയുടെ ബാല്യകാല പേര് ? ",
    "answerText": " ഹോലീഹ്ഷാഹ്‌ഷ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83182,
    "questionText": " The largest lake in India?",
    "answerText": " Chilka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83183,
    "questionText": " In which state is Chilka?",
    "answerText": " Odisha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83184,
    "questionText": " In which lake Break fast island and Honey moon island are situated?",
    "answerText": " Chilka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83185,
    "questionText": " നെൽസൺ മണ്ടേല അന്താരാഷ്ട്ര ദിനം? ",
    "answerText": " ജൂലായ് 18 "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83186,
    "questionText": " The founder of Royal Asiatic Society?",
    "answerText": " Warren Hastings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83187,
    "questionText": " In which year the incident responsible for Kakori Conspiracy Case was occured?",
    "answerText": 1925
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83188,
    "questionText": " ഇൻക്വിലാബ് സിന്ദാബാദ് എന്ന മുദ്രാവാക്യം ആദ്യമായി മുഴക്കിയത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഭഗത്‌സിങ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83189,
    "questionText": " സാരെ ജഹാംസെ അച്ഛാ എന്ന് ഉറുദുവിൽ എഴുതപ്പെട്ട ഗീതത്തിന്റെ കർത്താവ്? ",
    "answerText": " മുഹമ്മദ് ഇക്‌ബാൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83190,
    "questionText": " Who was the Viceroy of India during the Delhi Durbar of 1877?",
    "answerText": " Lytton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83191,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിൽ അച്ചടിക്കപ്പെട്ട ആദ്യ പുസ്തകമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോക്ട്രീന ക്രിസ്റ്റിന "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83192,
    "questionText": " The woman who faced trial along with Surya Sen?",
    "answerText": " Kalpana Joshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83193,
    "questionText": " Who attempted to assassinate Governor of Bengal Sir Stanley Jackson in a convocation ceremony?",
    "answerText": " Beena Das"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83194,
    "questionText": " The year of Jallianwala Bagh Tragedy?",
    "answerText": 1919
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83195,
    "questionText": " Who coined the slogan ‘Inquilab Zindabad’?",
    "answerText": " Muhammad Iqbal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83196,
    "questionText": " അച്ചടി യന്ത്രം കണ്ടുപിടിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഗുട്ടൻബർഗ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83197,
    "questionText": " Hindustan Republican Association was formed in 1924 at?",
    "answerText": " Kanpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83198,
    "questionText": " Aurobindo Ghosh was trialed in connection with .....conspiracy case?",
    "answerText": " Alipore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83199,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യൻ ബഹിരാകാശ ഗവേഷണ സ്ഥാപനം? ",
    "answerText": " ഐ.എസ്.ആർ.ഒ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83200,
    "questionText": " The first political organisation in modern India was founded in 1838. What was its name?",
    "answerText": " Landholder’s Association"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83201,
    "questionText": " The founder of Asiatic Society of Bengal in 1784?",
    "answerText": " William Jones"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83202,
    "questionText": " ഐ.ആർ.എസ് സാറ്റ്‌ലൈറ്റുകൾ വിക്ഷേപിക്കാൻ ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്ന വാഹനമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " പി.എസ്.എൽ.വി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83203,
    "questionText": " ഐ.എസ്.ആർ.ഒ സാറ്റ്‌ലൈറ്റ് സെന്റർ? ",
    "answerText": " ബാംഗ്ളൂർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83204,
    "questionText": " Who killed Michael O’Dyer to revenge for the Jallian Walla Bagh Massacre?",
    "answerText": " Uddham Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83205,
    "questionText": " Who raised the slogan ‘Inquilab Zindabad’ for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Bhagat Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83206,
    "questionText": " Who was called ‘the mother of Indian Revelution’?",
    "answerText": " Madam Bhikaji Kama"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83207,
    "questionText": " The year of foundation of Muslim League?",
    "answerText": 1906
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83208,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘Masterda’?",
    "answerText": " Surya Sen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83209,
    "questionText": " ബഹിരാകാശ വാഹനങ്ങളിൽ വളർത്തുന്ന സസ്യമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ക്ളോറെല്ല "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83210,
    "questionText": " The founder of Indian League in 1875?",
    "answerText": " Shishirkumar Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83211,
    "questionText": " ആദ്യമായി ബഹിരാകാശത്ത് എത്തി ഭൂമിയെ പ്രദക്ഷിണം വച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " യൂറി ഗഗാറിൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83212,
    "questionText": " The founder of Satyashodhak Samaj in 1873?",
    "answerText": " Jyotiba Phule"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83213,
    "questionText": " ബഹിരാകാശത്ത് എത്തിയ ആദ്യ വനിത? ",
    "answerText": " വാലന്റീന തെരഷ്കോവ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83214,
    "questionText": " The year of Naval Mutiny?",
    "answerText": 1946
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83215,
    "questionText": " ബഹിരാകാശത്ത് നടന്ന ആദ്യ വനിത? ",
    "answerText": " സെറ്റ്‌ലാന സവിറ്റ്‌സ്കിയ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83216,
    "questionText": " Who was the Viceroy when Indian National Congress was formed in 1885?",
    "answerText": " Dufferin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83217,
    "questionText": " Who founded Rashtriya Swayam Sevak Sangh in 1925?",
    "answerText": " Hedgewar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83218,
    "questionText": " ബഹിരാകാശയാത്ര നടത്തിയ രണ്ടാമത്തെ ഇന്ത്യൻ വംശജ? ",
    "answerText": " സുനിത വില്യംസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83219,
    "questionText": " The organisation founded by GG Agarkar, Mahadev Govind Ranade and VG Chiplunkar in 1885?",
    "answerText": " Deccan Education Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83220,
    "questionText": " In whicy year Vivekananda attended the World Parliament of Religions at Chicago?",
    "answerText": 1893
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83221,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘Shahid-i-Hind’?",
    "answerText": " Bhagat Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83222,
    "questionText": " Muhammadan Literary Society of Calcutta was founded by?",
    "answerText": " Nawab Abdul Latif"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83223,
    "questionText": " The founder of East India Association in 1866?",
    "answerText": " Dadabhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83224,
    "questionText": " Which organisation was founded by Anand Mohan Bose and Surendra Nath Bannerjee in 1876?",
    "answerText": " Indian Association"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83225,
    "questionText": " Who founded Indian Liberal Federation in 1918?",
    "answerText": " Surendra Nath Bannerjee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83226,
    "questionText": " Which was the second British Presidency in India?",
    "answerText": " Madras"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83227,
    "questionText": " Who founded Servants of India Society in 1905?",
    "answerText": " Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83228,
    "questionText": " Who founded Social Service League in 1911?",
    "answerText": " N.M.Joshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83229,
    "questionText": " Who laid the foundation of the Indian Patriotic Association in 1888?",
    "answerText": " Syed Ahmed Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83230,
    "questionText": " By which of the following for the first time, British government recognized the “Right of Dominion” for India?",
    "answerText": " Cripp’s Mission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83231,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of Khudai Khitmatgars (Servants of God)?",
    "answerText": " Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83232,
    "questionText": " Who founded Bharatiya Vidhya Bhavan in 1938?",
    "answerText": " K.M.Munshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83233,
    "questionText": " The publication launched by Bal Gangadhar Tilak in Marathi language?",
    "answerText": " Kesari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83234,
    "questionText": " The founder of Atmiya Sabha and Brahmasamaj?",
    "answerText": " Raja Ram Mohun Roy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83235,
    "questionText": " Who started the journals ‘Al Hilal’ and ‘Al Balal’?",
    "answerText": " Abul Kalam Azad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83236,
    "questionText": " The publication started by Mahathma Gandhi in South Africa?",
    "answerText": " Indian Opinion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83237,
    "questionText": " The retired British civil servant who was instrumental in the formation of Indian National Congress in 1885?",
    "answerText": " A.O.Hume"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83238,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy when Sharda Act, which raised the marriageable age, was passed?",
    "answerText": " Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83239,
    "questionText": " The author of ‘Arctic Home in the Vedas’?",
    "answerText": " Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83240,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who established two colleges for the education and political training of the Indian Princes?",
    "answerText": " Mayo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83241,
    "questionText": " Who founded Muslim League in 1906?",
    "answerText": " Aga Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83242,
    "questionText": " The river that originates from Aravalli hills near Ajmer in Rajastan?",
    "answerText": " Luni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83243,
    "questionText": " In which state are Ajanta and Ellora caves?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83244,
    "questionText": " Where is Taj Mahal?",
    "answerText": " Agra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83245,
    "questionText": " Which dynasty constructed the Mahabalipuram Monuments in Tamil Nadu?",
    "answerText": " Pallavas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83246,
    "questionText": " In which state is Manas Wild Life Sanctuary?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83247,
    "questionText": " Churches and Convents of Goa were built during the colonial rule of the?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83248,
    "questionText": " Great Himalaya ranges are also known as?",
    "answerText": " Himadri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83249,
    "questionText": " Lesser Himalayas are also known as?",
    "answerText": " Himachal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83250,
    "questionText": " Outer Himalaya ranges are known as?",
    "answerText": " Shiwalik"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83251,
    "questionText": " The oldest mountain ranges in India?",
    "answerText": " Aravallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83252,
    "questionText": " The highest peak in Aravallis?",
    "answerText": " Gurusikhar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83253,
    "questionText": " Hemavati, Amaravati, Bhavani, Kabani, Noyal are the important tributaries of?",
    "answerText": " Kaveri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83254,
    "questionText": " Mandovi is an important river in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83255,
    "questionText": " The youngest mountain ranges in India?",
    "answerText": " Himalayas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83256,
    "questionText": " River flows between Vindhya and Satpura?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83257,
    "questionText": " Ken is a tributary of which river?",
    "answerText": " Yamuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83258,
    "questionText": " The mountain range that separates North India and South India?",
    "answerText": " Vindhyas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83259,
    "questionText": " Western Ghats and Eastern Ghats meet at?",
    "answerText": " Nilgiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83260,
    "questionText": " In which state Khasi and Garo Hills are situated?",
    "answerText": " Meghalaya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83261,
    "questionText": " In which part of India, Patkai ranges situated?",
    "answerText": " Eastern"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83262,
    "questionText": " In which state is Lushai Hills?",
    "answerText": " Mizoram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83263,
    "questionText": " The name Mount Everest was given by?",
    "answerText": " Andrew Waugh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83264,
    "questionText": " Everest was named after Sir George Everest who was the ....... of India?",
    "answerText": " Surveyor General"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83265,
    "questionText": " The highest peak in India as per the records of the govt of India?",
    "answerText": " Godwin Austin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83266,
    "questionText": " The highest peak in undisputed Indian territory is Kanchenjunga(8598m). It is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83267,
    "questionText": " Where is Godwin Austin (K2 0 or Qagir) is now situated?",
    "answerText": " Pak occupied Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83268,
    "questionText": " The height of Godwin Austin is ...... m?",
    "answerText": 8611
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83269,
    "questionText": " The river that covers the longest distance in India?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83270,
    "questionText": " In Nepal, Everest is known as?",
    "answerText": " Sagarmatha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83271,
    "questionText": " What is known as Chomolungma in Tibet?",
    "answerText": " Everest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83272,
    "questionText": " What is the height of Mount Everest, the highest peak in the world?",
    "answerText": " 8848m"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83273,
    "questionText": " Everest was identified as the highest peak in the world by?",
    "answerText": " Radhanath Sikthar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83274,
    "questionText": " Ganga originates in?",
    "answerText": " Gangotri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83275,
    "questionText": " Ganga flows through the states of Uttarakhand, Uttar Pradesh, Bihar and.......?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83276,
    "questionText": " Ganga drains into?",
    "answerText": " Bay of Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83277,
    "questionText": " The head streams of Ganga are Bhagirathi and?",
    "answerText": " Alakananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83278,
    "questionText": " Ganga and Yamuna meet at?",
    "answerText": " Allahabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83279,
    "questionText": " The place of Triveni Sangamam where Ganga, Yamuna and mythical Saraswathy meet?",
    "answerText": " Allahabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83280,
    "questionText": " The largest tributary of Ganga?",
    "answerText": " Yamuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83281,
    "questionText": " Ganga covers the longest distance in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83282,
    "questionText": " Beyond the Farakka, Ganga is known as?",
    "answerText": " Padma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83283,
    "questionText": " Name the legendary charecter who is believed to have brought Ganga to Earth?",
    "answerText": " Bhagiratha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83284,
    "questionText": " The distributary of Ganga flows through West Bengal?",
    "answerText": " Bhagirathi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83285,
    "questionText": " After joining Jalangi, Bhagirathi is known as?",
    "answerText": " Hoogly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83286,
    "questionText": " Rabindra Setu, Vidhyasagar Setu and Vivekananda Setu are built across?",
    "answerText": " Hoogly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83287,
    "questionText": " On the banks of which river is Kolkata?",
    "answerText": " Hoogly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83288,
    "questionText": " In which state is Farakka barrage?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83289,
    "questionText": " Farrakka barrage is built across?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83290,
    "questionText": " The Farrakka barrage is built to protect the ...... port?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83291,
    "questionText": " The Mahathma Gandhi Setu, the longest river bridge in India is built across?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83292,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest delta in the world?",
    "answerText": " GangaBrahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83293,
    "questionText": " The river island Majuli is in?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83294,
    "questionText": " Which river was known as Vitasta in ancient times?",
    "answerText": " Jhulum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83295,
    "questionText": " Which river was known an Aksini in ancient times?",
    "answerText": " Chenab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83296,
    "questionText": " Parushni was the ancient name of?",
    "answerText": " Ravi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83297,
    "questionText": " Ancient name of Beas?",
    "answerText": " Vipas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83298,
    "questionText": " Which river was known as Satadru?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83299,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Red river’ in India?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83300,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Sorrow of Bihar’?",
    "answerText": " Kosi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83301,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Sorrow of Assam’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83302,
    "questionText": " Meghna is a distributary of?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83303,
    "questionText": " The river that originates in the northern slopes of Kailas range in India near the Mansarovar lake?",
    "answerText": " Indus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83304,
    "questionText": " The longest tributaty of Indus, flowing through India?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83305,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as Siang, Dihang in Arunachal Pradesh?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83306,
    "questionText": " The river that was declared as the national river of India?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83307,
    "questionText": " Yamuna was known as ...... in Puranas?",
    "answerText": " Kalindi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83308,
    "questionText": " Betwa is a tributaty of which river?",
    "answerText": " Yamuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83309,
    "questionText": " Which river in India has the greatest flow of water?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83310,
    "questionText": " Jhulum, Chenab, Ravi, Beas and Sutlej are the tribuataries of?",
    "answerText": " Indus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83311,
    "questionText": " The longest west flowing river in India?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83312,
    "questionText": " Yamuna originates from Yamunotri in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83313,
    "questionText": " Which is known as Tsangpo in Tibet?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83314,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as the ‘life line of Sikkim’?",
    "answerText": " Tista"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83315,
    "questionText": " The largest river basin in India?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83316,
    "questionText": " The speediest river in India?",
    "answerText": " Tista"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83317,
    "questionText": " The second longest river in India?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83318,
    "questionText": " Tungabhadra, Bhima, Malaprabha, Koyna, Musi are the important tributaries of?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83319,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Sorrow of Orissa’?",
    "answerText": " Mahanadi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83320,
    "questionText": " Taj Mahal is on the banks of which river?",
    "answerText": " Yamuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83321,
    "questionText": " In which state Mahanadi originates?",
    "answerText": " Chhatisgarh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83322,
    "questionText": " The longest river in South India?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83323,
    "questionText": " The river that originates from Brahmagiri Hills in Coorg district of Karnataka?",
    "answerText": " Kaveri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83324,
    "questionText": " The river which originates from Triambak Hills in Nasik district in Maharashtra?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83325,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Dakshina Ganga’?",
    "answerText": " Kaveri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83326,
    "questionText": " The second longest west flowing river in India?",
    "answerText": " Tapti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83327,
    "questionText": " The river that originates from the Amarkantak hills in Madhya Pradesh?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83328,
    "questionText": " The longest rift valley river in India?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83329,
    "questionText": " Which river originates from Mahabaleswar hills in Maharashtra?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83330,
    "questionText": " Which river originates from Betul district in Madhya Pradesh?",
    "answerText": " Tapti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83331,
    "questionText": " Which Indian river is known as salt river?",
    "answerText": " Luni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83332,
    "questionText": " The longest river in Indian peninsula?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83333,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as the twin or handmaid of Narmada?",
    "answerText": " Tapti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83334,
    "questionText": " Which river finally lost in the marshy grounds of Rann of Kuchchh?",
    "answerText": " Luni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83335,
    "questionText": " Tapti, Narmada, Mahi and Sabarmati drains into?",
    "answerText": " Gulf of Cambay"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83336,
    "questionText": " Khajuraho Temples are in Madhya Pradesh. These were built by the dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Chandellas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83337,
    "questionText": " Indravati, Manjira,Veinganga, Sabari,Purna are the important tributaries of?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83338,
    "questionText": " Fatepur Sikri in Uttar Pradesh was built by ...... as his capital?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83339,
    "questionText": " Brihadiswara Temple at Tanjavur is also known as Rajarajeswara temple. It was built by?",
    "answerText": " Cholas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83340,
    "questionText": " Nandadevi National Park is in?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83341,
    "questionText": " The largest brackish water lake in India?",
    "answerText": " Chilka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83342,
    "questionText": " Pulikat lake is situated in?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83343,
    "questionText": " The island that separates Pulikat lake from Bay of Bengal?",
    "answerText": " Sriharikota"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83344,
    "questionText": " Which lake in India is famous for prawn cultivation?",
    "answerText": " Chilka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83345,
    "questionText": " In which state is Kolleru lake?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83346,
    "questionText": " The largest lake in South India?",
    "answerText": " Kolleru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83347,
    "questionText": " In which state is Wular lake?",
    "answerText": " Jammu & Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83348,
    "questionText": " The only crator lake in India?",
    "answerText": " Lonar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83349,
    "questionText": " In which state is Lonar lake?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83350,
    "questionText": " In which state is Nalsarovar lake?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83351,
    "questionText": " The saltiest lake in India?",
    "answerText": " Sambhar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83352,
    "questionText": " In which state is Sambhar lake?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83353,
    "questionText": " In which state is Loktak lake?",
    "answerText": " Manipur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83354,
    "questionText": " The largest lake in north east India?",
    "answerText": " Loktak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83355,
    "questionText": " Dhootsagar waterfalls is in...... river?",
    "answerText": " Mandovi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83356,
    "questionText": " The highest water fall in India?",
    "answerText": " Jog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83357,
    "questionText": " Jog falls is also known as?",
    "answerText": " Jersoppa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83358,
    "questionText": " In which river is Jog falls?",
    "answerText": " Sharavati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83359,
    "questionText": " In which state is Jog falls?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83360,
    "questionText": " In which state is Shivasamudram water falls?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83361,
    "questionText": " In which state is Hogenackal water falls?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83362,
    "questionText": " In which state is Chitrakot waterfalls?",
    "answerText": " Chhatisgarh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83363,
    "questionText": " Almora which is situated on Kumaon Hills is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83364,
    "questionText": " Cherrapunji situated in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Meghalaya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83365,
    "questionText": " Coonoor which is situated on Nilgiri Hills is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83366,
    "questionText": " The hill station Dalhousie is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83367,
    "questionText": " In which state is Darjeeling?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83368,
    "questionText": " Gulmarg is a hill station in?",
    "answerText": " Jammu & Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83369,
    "questionText": " In which state is Kasauli hill station?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83370,
    "questionText": " Which is known as ‘the princess of hill stations’?",
    "answerText": " Kodaikanal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83371,
    "questionText": " The Queen of hill stations in South India?",
    "answerText": " Udagamandalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83372,
    "questionText": " In which state is Mahabaleswar?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83373,
    "questionText": " The only hill station in Rajastan?",
    "answerText": " Mount Abu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83374,
    "questionText": " Mussoorie is a hill station in........ where the Lal Bahadur Shastri Academy of Administration is situated?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83375,
    "questionText": " Nainital is a hill station which is also the seat of High Court of?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83376,
    "questionText": " Which hill station in Madhya Pradesh is known as ‘Queen of Satpuras’?",
    "answerText": " Pachmarhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83377,
    "questionText": " Ranikhet is a hill station in?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83378,
    "questionText": " Ranchi is a hill station in?",
    "answerText": " Jharkhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83379,
    "questionText": " The state capital in India situated in the highest altitude?",
    "answerText": " Shimla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83380,
    "questionText": " Yercaud is a hill station in ...... in Shevaroy Hills?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83381,
    "questionText": " In which state is Coorg?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83382,
    "questionText": " The highest hill station in South India?",
    "answerText": " Udagamandalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83383,
    "questionText": " The only hill resort developed by Americans in India?",
    "answerText": " Kodaikanal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83384,
    "questionText": " The hill station discovered by John Sullivan?",
    "answerText": " Udagamandalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83385,
    "questionText": " The Botanical gardens established by the Marquis of Tweed dale in 1847, is at?",
    "answerText": " Udagamandalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83386,
    "questionText": " Dharmasthala is a hill station in?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83387,
    "questionText": " Kalimpong is a hill station in?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83388,
    "questionText": " The National Highway Authority of India was started functioning in?",
    "answerText": 1995
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83389,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of the National Highway authority of India is?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83390,
    "questionText": " Which state has the longest coverage of national highways?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83391,
    "questionText": " Which state has the least length of national highways?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83392,
    "questionText": " The state with the largest number of national highways?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83393,
    "questionText": " Cities connected by the Golden Quadrilateral project are New Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata and .....?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83394,
    "questionText": " The North-South corridor connects Srinagar and .......?",
    "answerText": " Kanyakumari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83395,
    "questionText": " The West-East corridor connects Porbander and .......?",
    "answerText": " Silchar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83396,
    "questionText": " Border Roads Organisation was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1960
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83397,
    "questionText": " The national highway which is not connected to other national highways?",
    "answerText": " NH 223 (old name)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83398,
    "questionText": " The longest national highway in India (NH 44) connects Srinagar and?",
    "answerText": " Kanyakumari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83399,
    "questionText": " The first air conditioned bus stop in India?",
    "answerText": " Bangalore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83400,
    "questionText": " The first rapid transit system in India was established at...... in 1854?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83401,
    "questionText": " The cheapest mode of transport in India?",
    "answerText": " Water transport"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83402,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of the Inland Waterway authority of India is?",
    "answerText": " Noida"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83403,
    "questionText": " National waterway -1 connects Allahabad and......?",
    "answerText": " Haldia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83404,
    "questionText": " The father of space research in India?",
    "answerText": " Vikram Sarabhai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83405,
    "questionText": " ഇലയിലെ ജാലികാസിരാവിന്യാസത്തിനുദാഹരണമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " പ്ളാവ്, മാവ്, ആൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83406,
    "questionText": " വേര് വലിച്ചെടുക്കുന്ന ജലവും ലവണങ്ങളും എല്ലാ ഭാഗത്തും എത്തിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " സൈലം കുഴലുകൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83407,
    "questionText": " തറയിൽ പടർന്നു വളരുന്ന സസ്യങ്ങൾ? ",
    "answerText": " ഇഴവള്ളികൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83408,
    "questionText": " Indian National Committee for Space Research (INCOSPAR) was established in?",
    "answerText": 1962
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83409,
    "questionText": " ഭൂഗുരുത്വാകർഷണത്തിന്റെ ദിശയിൽ വളരാനുള്ള സസ്യത്തിന്റെ പ്രവണത? ",
    "answerText": " ജിയോട്രോപ്പിസം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83410,
    "questionText": " Space Science and Technology Centre was established at Thumba in?",
    "answerText": 1965
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83411,
    "questionText": " ഇലകളുടെ അരികിലുള്ള ജലരന്ധ്രങ്ങൾ വഴി ജലം തുള്ളികളായി നഷ്ടപ്പെടുന്ന പ്രക്രിയ? ",
    "answerText": " ബിന്ദുസ്രാവം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83412,
    "questionText": " നാഡീവ്യവസ്ഥയില്ലാത്ത ജീവി വർഗം? ",
    "answerText": " പോറിഫെറ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83413,
    "questionText": " ഏറ്റവും കട്ടിയുള്ള ത്വക്ക് ഏത് ജീവിക്കാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " തിമിംഗല സ്രാവ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83414,
    "questionText": " ഏറ്റവും വലിയ പൊക്കമുള്ള സപുഷ്പി? ",
    "answerText": " യൂക്കാലിപ്റ്റസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83415,
    "questionText": " ബാഷ്‌പരൂപത്തിൽ സസ്യങ്ങളിൽ നിന്ന് ജലം നഷ്ടപ്പെടുന്ന പ്രക്രിയ? ",
    "answerText": " സസ്യസ്വേദനം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83416,
    "questionText": " രക്താർബുദത്തിന്റെ ചികിത്സയ്ക്കായി ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്ന ഔഷധം? ",
    "answerText": " വിൻക്രിസ്റ്റിൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83417,
    "questionText": " സസ്യശരീരം കോശങ്ങളാൽ നിർമ്മിതമാണെന്ന് കണ്ടെത്തിയത്? ",
    "answerText": " എം.ജെ. ഷ്‌ളീഡൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83418,
    "questionText": " പാരമ്പര്യസ്വഭാവങ്ങൾ തലമുറ തലമുറ വ്യാപിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡി.എൻ.എ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83419,
    "questionText": " ആൽഗകളെക്കുറിച്ചുള്ള പഠനം? ",
    "answerText": " ഫൈക്കോളജി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83420,
    "questionText": " പൊക്കിൾക്കൊടി ഗർഭാശയഭിത്തിയിൽ യോജിക്കുന്ന ഭാഗം? ",
    "answerText": " പ്ളാസന്റ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83421,
    "questionText": " പ്രതിസ്വേദനമായി ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്ന രാസപദാർത്ഥം? ",
    "answerText": " അബ്‌സിസിക്കാഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83422,
    "questionText": " മണ്ണിലെ നൈട്രജൻ സ്ഥിതീകരണ ബാക്ടീരിയ? ",
    "answerText": " അസറ്റോബാക്ടർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83423,
    "questionText": " പ്രാചീന രസതന്ത്രത്തിന് ആൽകെമി എന്ന പേരു നൽകിയത്? ",
    "answerText": " അറബികൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83424,
    "questionText": " ആന്റിബയോട്ടിക്കുകൾ കഴിക്കുമ്പോൾ അത് ഏതിലാണ് ആഗിരണം ചെയ്യപ്പെടുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " ശരീരത്തിലെ പ്രോട്ടീനുകളിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83425,
    "questionText": " Indian Space Research Organisation was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1969
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83426,
    "questionText": " ഒരു ഫലത്തിന്റെ മൂന്നു ഭാഗങ്ങൾ? ",
    "answerText": " ബാഹ്യകഞ്ചുകം, മദ്ധ്യകഞ്ചുകം, ആന്തരകഞ്ചുകം, ഇവ മൂന്നും ചേർന്നുണ്ടായിട്ടുള്ള ഫലകഞ്ചുകം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83427,
    "questionText": " അമ്ളമഴയിലെ പ്രധാന ഘടകം? ",
    "answerText": " ഹൈഡ്രോക്ളോറിക്കാസിഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83428,
    "questionText": " റബർ പാൽ ഉറയ്ക്കാതിരിക്കാൻ ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " അമോണിയ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83429,
    "questionText": " കണ്ണാടിയിൽ രസം പൂശാൻ ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " ടിൻ അമാൽഗം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83430,
    "questionText": " മനുഷ്യൻ കഴിച്ചാൽ ദഹിക്കാത്ത അന്നജം? ",
    "answerText": " സെല്ലുലോസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83431,
    "questionText": " Indian Space Commission and Department of Space was established in?",
    "answerText": 1972
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83432,
    "questionText": " അന്തരീക്ഷ വായുവിലേക്ക് ഉയരുന്ന ബലൂൺ പൊട്ടുന്നത് ഏത് നിയമം അനുസരിച്ചാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ബോയിൽസ് നിയമം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83433,
    "questionText": " ആൺ - പെൺ ബീജകോശങ്ങൾ പ്രത്യേകം സസ്യങ്ങളിലുണ്ടാകുന്നുവെങ്കിൽ അത്തരം സസ്യങ്ങളെ എന്തുവിളിക്കും? ",
    "answerText": " ഏകലിംഗ സസ്യങ്ങൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83434,
    "questionText": " കാണ്ഡത്തിൽ നിന്ന് താഴേക്ക് വളരുന്ന ദണ്ഡുക്കൾ പോലുള്ള വേരുകൾ? ",
    "answerText": " പൊയ്‌ക്കാൽ വേരുകൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83435,
    "questionText": " സസ്യത്തിന്റെ വളർച്ചയുടെ ദിശ ഉദ്ദീപന ദിശയിലേക്കാണെങ്കിൽ അത് നിശ്ചിത ട്രോപ്പിക ചലനമാണ്. നേരെ വിപരീതമായ ചലനം? ",
    "answerText": " നിഷേധ ട്രോപ്പിക ചലനം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83436,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of ISRO (Anthareeksh Bhavan)?",
    "answerText": " Bangalore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83437,
    "questionText": " മുളയുടെ ശാസ്ത്രീയ നാമം ? ",
    "answerText": " ബാംബൂസ് ബാബോസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83438,
    "questionText": " ഹരിതകത്തിൽ അടങ്ങിയിരിക്കുന്ന ലോഹം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " മഗ്നീഷ്യം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83439,
    "questionText": " സസ്യങ്ങളിൽ കാണുന്ന പച്ച നിറം? ",
    "answerText": " ഹരിതകണം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83440,
    "questionText": " രാജവെമ്പാലയുടെ ശാസ്ത്രീയ നാമം? ",
    "answerText": " ഒഫിയോഫറസ് ഹന്ന "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83441,
    "questionText": " To which organisation Thumba Equatorial Rocket Launching Station (TERLS) is dedicated (1968)?",
    "answerText": " UNO"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83442,
    "questionText": " എന്താണ് നാസ്റ്റിക് ചലനങ്ങൾ? ",
    "answerText": " സസ്യങ്ങളുടെ ചലനങ്ങൾക്ക് ഉദ്ദീപനത്തിന്റെ ദിശയുമായി യാതൊരു ബന്ധമില്ലാത്തതിനെയാണ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83443,
    "questionText": " The first rocket launched from TERLS?",
    "answerText": " Nike Apache"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83444,
    "questionText": " ഹരിതക നിർമ്മിതിക്കാവശ്യമായത്? ",
    "answerText": " സൂര്യപ്രകാശം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83445,
    "questionText": " ജാതിക്കയുടെ ശാസ്ത്രീയ നാമം ? ",
    "answerText": " മിറിസ്റ്റിക്ക ഫ്രാഗ്രൻസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83446,
    "questionText": " എന്താണ് പരാദസസ്യം? ",
    "answerText": " മറ്റു സസ്യങ്ങളിൽ വളർന്ന് അവയിൽ നിന്ന് ആഹാരവും ജലവും വലിച്ചെടുക്കുന്നത് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83447,
    "questionText": " പക്ഷിപ്പനി വൈറസ് ആദ്യമായി കണ്ടെത്തിയത്? ",
    "answerText": " ബീജിങ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83448,
    "questionText": " സസ്തനികളുടെ കഴുത്തിലെ കശേരുക്കളുടെ എണ്ണം? ",
    "answerText": 7
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83449,
    "questionText": " Chandrayan I, India’s first mission to moon was launched on 22nd October, 2008 from?",
    "answerText": " Sriharikota"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83450,
    "questionText": " Where is Satish Dhawan Space Centre?",
    "answerText": " Sriharikota"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83451,
    "questionText": " Vikram Sarabhai Space Centre is at?",
    "answerText": " Thiruvananthapuram (Thumba)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83452,
    "questionText": " The first Indian cosmonaut Rakesh Sharma went to space (1984 April )in a space vehicle named?",
    "answerText": " Soyuz T-11"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83453,
    "questionText": " The first satellite launched by India on 19th April, 1975?",
    "answerText": " Aryabhatta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83454,
    "questionText": " Name the space vehicle used for the launching of Aryabhatta?",
    "answerText": " Cosmos"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83455,
    "questionText": " India launched its second satellite Bhaskara I in?",
    "answerText": 1979
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83456,
    "questionText": " INSAT 1A was launched in?",
    "answerText": 1982
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83457,
    "questionText": " The first Indian satellite launched from India (1980 July 18)?",
    "answerText": " Rohini"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83458,
    "questionText": " Metsat-1 which was later renamed Kalpana-I launched on 2nd September,.......?",
    "answerText": 2002
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83459,
    "questionText": " EDUSAT, India’s first educational satellite was launched in?",
    "answerText": 2004
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83460,
    "questionText": " India launched experimental communication satellite APPLE (Ariane Passenger Payload Experiment) in?",
    "answerText": 1981
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83461,
    "questionText": " Antrix Corporation, the commercial undertaking of Space Department, was established in?",
    "answerText": 1992
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83462,
    "questionText": " Headquarters of the Antrix Corporation?",
    "answerText": " Bangalore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83463,
    "questionText": " In which state is Sriharikota?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83464,
    "questionText": " Department of Ocean Development was created in?",
    "answerText": 1981
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83465,
    "questionText": " The first Indian team to Antarctica left India in the year?",
    "answerText": 1981
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83466,
    "questionText": " The first Indian team to Antarctica reached the destination in the year?",
    "answerText": 1982
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83467,
    "questionText": " India was admitted as a consultative member in the Antarctica Treaty system of 1959 in the year?",
    "answerText": " 1983......"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83468,
    "questionText": " India became a member of Scientific Committee on Antarctica Research in?",
    "answerText": 1984
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83469,
    "questionText": " Who led the first Indian expedition team to Antarctica?",
    "answerText": " SZ Qasim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83470,
    "questionText": " Name the vehicle used by the first Indian expedition team to Antarctica?",
    "answerText": " MV Polar Circle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83471,
    "questionText": " The first Indian expedition to Antarctica started voyage from?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83472,
    "questionText": " The first Indian post office outside Indian territory was opened in Antarctica in the year?",
    "answerText": 1983
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83473,
    "questionText": " The first Indian research station in Antarctica, the construction of which was completed in 1984?",
    "answerText": " Dakshin Gangotri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83474,
    "questionText": " The second Indian research station in Antarctica which was commissioned in 1989?",
    "answerText": " Maitri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83475,
    "questionText": " India’s third permanent research station in Antarctica which is under construction?",
    "answerText": " Bharati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83476,
    "questionText": " The post office in Antarctica comes under the jurisdiction of...... postal circle?",
    "answerText": " Goa."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83477,
    "questionText": " In which year Panchayat Raj system was introduced in Rajastan?",
    "answerText": 1959
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83478,
    "questionText": " In which state the major part of the Western Ghats lies?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83479,
    "questionText": " Which religion belongs to the Lotus Temple in New Delhi?",
    "answerText": " Bahai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83480,
    "questionText": " In which Indian State Pahari language is spoken?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83481,
    "questionText": " Where Rajiv Gandhi was born?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83482,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of CAPART(Council for Advancedment of People’s Action and Rural Technology)?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83483,
    "questionText": " Suisini is a folk dance of which Indian state?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83484,
    "questionText": " The first city in India where radio broadcasting was started?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83485,
    "questionText": " In which state is Keonjhar Iron ore mines?",
    "answerText": " Odisha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83486,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state is Chabali iron ore?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83487,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state is Bhilwara silver mines?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83488,
    "questionText": " The State in India which has the largest number of Local Self Government Institutions?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83489,
    "questionText": " Which is the smallest district in the Indian Union?",
    "answerText": " Mahe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83490,
    "questionText": " Arhai Din Ka Jhonpara, a mosque constructed during the period of Slave rulers, was situated at?",
    "answerText": " Ajmer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83491,
    "questionText": " Gopinath Bordoloi was an eminent freedom fighter and recipient of Bharat Ratna, belonged to the State of?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83492,
    "questionText": " Amarnath is a holy place for?",
    "answerText": " Hindus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83493,
    "questionText": " Lepchas are the tribal people in?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83494,
    "questionText": " Which is called ‘the Pearl Harbour of India’?",
    "answerText": " Tutucorin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83495,
    "questionText": " The second largest Union Territory in India, in terms of area?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83496,
    "questionText": " The most widely spoken foreign language in India?",
    "answerText": " English"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83497,
    "questionText": " The biggest state-run organisation in India?",
    "answerText": " Railways"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83498,
    "questionText": " The parent script of the Indo-Aryan and Dravidian languages?",
    "answerText": " Brahmi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83499,
    "questionText": " Where is National Institute of Nutrition?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83500,
    "questionText": " In which state is Zawar mines?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83501,
    "questionText": " In which state is Almora hill station?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83502,
    "questionText": " The coastline of India including those of the islands is?",
    "answerText": " 7516.6 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83503,
    "questionText": " In which country Arakan Yoma ,an extension of Himalayas located?",
    "answerText": " Myanmar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83504,
    "questionText": " The State which instituted the Kanshi Ram Sports Award?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83505,
    "questionText": " ജനസംഖ്യ ഏറ്റവും കുറഞ്ഞ ഭൂഖണ്ഡം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ആസ്ട്രേലിയ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83506,
    "questionText": " The mountain range between Narmada and Tapti?",
    "answerText": " Satpura"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83507,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തിലെ ഏറ്റവും ജനസംഖ്യ കൂടിയ ദ്വീപ്? ",
    "answerText": " ജാവ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83508,
    "questionText": " Which State has the lowest number of Members in the Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83509,
    "questionText": " ജനസംഖ്യ ഏറ്റവും കുറഞ്ഞ പട്ടണം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " യമൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83510,
    "questionText": " ഏറ്റവും കൂടുതൽ ജനസംഖ്യയുള്ള ആഫ്രിക്കൻ രാജ്യം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " നൈജീരിയ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83511,
    "questionText": " In which state is Bhilai Steel Plant?",
    "answerText": " Chhatisgarh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83512,
    "questionText": " The highest peak in Pakistan?",
    "answerText": " Tirich Mir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83513,
    "questionText": " ജനസംഖ്യയെക്കുറിച്ചുള്ള പഠനം? ",
    "answerText": " ഡെമോഗ്രഫി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83514,
    "questionText": " ആയുർദൈർഘ്യത്തിൽ പിന്നാക്കം നിൽക്കുന്ന രാജ്യം? ",
    "answerText": " സ്വാസിലാൻഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83515,
    "questionText": " To which mineral ‘Raniganj’ is associated?",
    "answerText": " Coal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83516,
    "questionText": " The National Institute of Visually Handicapped is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Dehra Dun"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83517,
    "questionText": " Which Indian state has the largest number of Loksabha seats?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83518,
    "questionText": " അന്താരാഷ്ട്ര വൃദ്ധവർഷമായി ആചരിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": 1999
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83519,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തെ ആദ്യത്തെ ബാങ്ക് ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " റോയൽ ബാങ്ക് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83520,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji spent 2089 days in Indian prisons. Where was his last confinement?",
    "answerText": " Aga Khan Palace; Pune"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83521,
    "questionText": " ബിൽ ഒഫ് എക്സ്‌ചേഞ്ചുകൾ സ്വീകരിക്കുകയും ലോണുകൾ, സെക്യൂരിറ്റികൾ എന്നിവ കൈകാര്യം ചെയ്യുകയും ചെയ്യുന്ന ബാങ്കുകൾ? ",
    "answerText": " മർച്ചന്റ് ബാങ്കുകൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83522,
    "questionText": " തന്റെ കടബാദ്ധ്യത തീർക്കാൻ കഴിവില്ലായെന്ന് ഒരു വ്യക്തി നിയമപരമായി പ്രഖ്യാപിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " പാപ്പരത്തം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83523,
    "questionText": " ലഘുവായ്പകൾ എന്ന ആശയം ആദ്യമായി അവതരിപ്പിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " മുഹമ്മദ് യൂനുസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83524,
    "questionText": " The venue of first National Games held in 1985?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83525,
    "questionText": " റോയൽ ബാങ്ക് ആരംഭിച്ച വർഷം? ",
    "answerText": " 1728ൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83526,
    "questionText": " സെൻട്രൽ ബാങ്ക് പലിശ നിരക്ക് നിശ്ചയിക്കുന്നത് എന്തിന്റെ അടിസ്ഥാനത്തിലാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " വാണിജ്യ ബാങ്കിന് കൊടുക്കുന്ന വായ്പയുടെ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83527,
    "questionText": " To which language Tulu is belonged?",
    "answerText": " Dravidian"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83528,
    "questionText": " ആദ്യമായി ഗോൾഡ് സ്റ്റാൻഡേർഡ് സ്വീകരിച്ച രാജ്യം? ",
    "answerText": " ബ്രിട്ടൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83529,
    "questionText": " Chandranagar, a former European colony was added to the State of ……. in 1954?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83530,
    "questionText": " കറൻസി നോട്ടുകൾ, തപാൽമുദ്രകൾ എന്നിവ രൂപകല്പന ചെയ്തതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " തോമസ് റു "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83531,
    "questionText": " The most abundant fruit in India?",
    "answerText": " Mango"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83532,
    "questionText": " Govind Ballabh Pant University of Agriculture & Technology is the first agricultural university in India. It is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83533,
    "questionText": " പണപ്പെരുപ്പം നിയന്ത്രിക്കാനുള്ള മാർഗങ്ങൾ? ",
    "answerText": " ബാങ്ക് നിരക്ക് ഉയർത്തുക, വില നിയന്ത്രിക്കുക, അവശ്യ സാധനങ്ങൾ വിതരണം ചെയ്യുക, സർക്കാർ ചെലവ് കുറയ്ക്കുക "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83534,
    "questionText": " പേപ്പർ ഗോൾഡ് എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " സ്പെഷ്യൽ ഡ്രോയിംഗ് റൈറ്റ്‌സ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83535,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state is Dharavi, India’s largest slum?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83536,
    "questionText": " Which port city in India is situated in Salsette island?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83537,
    "questionText": " പ്ളാസ്റ്റിക് മണി എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " ക്രെഡിറ്റ് കാർഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83538,
    "questionText": " ഡോക്യുടെൽ മെഷീൻ നിർമ്മിച്ചതാര് ? ",
    "answerText": " ഡൊണാൾഡ് സി. വെറ്റ്‌സെൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83539,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയിലെ ആദ്യത്തെ എ.ടി.എം ആരംഭിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " മുംബയിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83540,
    "questionText": " Parameswarakund is a place of pilgrimage in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83541,
    "questionText": " During the epic period which region in India was known as ‘Pragjyotisha’?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83542,
    "questionText": " The first express way of India?",
    "answerText": " Ahmedabad-Vadodara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83543,
    "questionText": " വിദേശ നാണ്യ വിനിമയ വിപണിയിൽ ആവശ്യം കൂടുതലുള്ള കറൻസി? ",
    "answerText": " ഹാർഡ് കറൻസി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83544,
    "questionText": " ഒരു ധനകാര്യകേന്ദ്രത്തിൽ നിന്ന് മറ്റൊന്നിലേക്ക് കൂടുതൽ പലിശ തേടിപ്പോകുന്ന മൂലധനം? ",
    "answerText": " ഹോട്ട്‌മണി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83545,
    "questionText": " Veeresalingam was a reformer in?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83546,
    "questionText": " അമേരിക്കൻ സാമ്പത്തിക കേന്ദ്രമായ വാൾസ്ട്രീറ്റിൽ ഇപ്പോഴത്തെ സാമ്പത്തിക മാന്ദ്യത്തിന് തുടക്കം കുറിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " 2007ൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83547,
    "questionText": " കടബാദ്ധ്യതകൾ തീർക്കുന്നതിനായി ഗവൺമെന്റ് സ്വന്തം ലാഭത്തിൽനിന്ന് നീക്കിവയ്ക്കുന്ന തുക? ",
    "answerText": " സികിങ് ഫണ്ട് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83548,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തിലെ ആദ്യത്തെ ഇലക്ട്രോണിക്സ് വിപണി? ",
    "answerText": " അമേരിക്കയിലെ നാസ്ദാക്ക് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83549,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തിലെ ഏറ്റവും വലിയ ഓഹരി വിപണി ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ടോക്കിയോ (ജപ്പാൻ) "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83550,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തിലെ ആദ്യത്തെ ഓഹരി വിപണി ആരംഭിച്ചതെവിടെ? ",
    "answerText": " ബെൽജിയത്തിലെ ആൻവെർപ്പിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83551,
    "questionText": " ബിഗ് ബോഡ് എന്ന അപരനാമമുള്ളത്? ",
    "answerText": " ന്യൂയോർക്ക് സ്റ്റോക്ക് എക്സ്‌ചേഞ്ച് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83552,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘Socretes of Maharashtra’?",
    "answerText": " Gopalakrishna Gokhale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83553,
    "questionText": " The new name of Sudhamapuri?",
    "answerText": " Porbander"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83554,
    "questionText": " നാസ്‌ദാക്കിൽ ലിസ്റ്റ് ചെയ്യപ്പെട്ട ആദ്യത്തെ ഇന്ത്യൻ കമ്പനി? ",
    "answerText": " ഇൻഫോസിസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83555,
    "questionText": " The setting for Rudyard Kipling’s ‘Jungle Book’?",
    "answerText": " Kanha National Park"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83556,
    "questionText": " മൂന്നാം ലോക രാജ്യങ്ങളുടെ പ്രധാന സാമ്പത്തിക സംഘടനകൾ ഏതെല്ലാം? ",
    "answerText": " ജി - 15 ഉം ജി - 77 ഉം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83557,
    "questionText": " ജപ്പാനിലെ നാണയം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " യെൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83558,
    "questionText": " The Virupaksha Temple is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Hampi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83559,
    "questionText": " പൈനാവ് ഏത് ജില്ലയുടെ ആസ്ഥാനമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ഇടുക്കി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83560,
    "questionText": " The largest religion in Lakshadweep?",
    "answerText": " Islam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83561,
    "questionText": " പ്രപഞ്ചത്തിന്റെ ഇഷ്ടികകൾ എന്നു വിളിക്കുന്നത് എന്തിനെ? ",
    "answerText": " തന്മാത്രകൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83562,
    "questionText": " The oldest municipal corporation in India?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83563,
    "questionText": " Madurai is situated on the banks of the river?",
    "answerText": " Vaigai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83564,
    "questionText": " A hill station in India set up by Americans?",
    "answerText": " Kodaikanal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83565,
    "questionText": " Which type of land form is occupied by the largest portion of India?",
    "answerText": " Plains"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83566,
    "questionText": " കേരളത്തിലെ കളിമൺ നിക്ഷേപം കൂടുതലുള്ള പ്രദേശം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " കുണ്ടറ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83567,
    "questionText": " Which country has the world’s highest percentage of arable land to the total geographical area?",
    "answerText": " India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83568,
    "questionText": " ബലൂൺ കണ്ടുപിടിച്ചതാര്? ",
    "answerText": " മോണ്ടോഗോൾഫിയൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83569,
    "questionText": " ജീവശാസ്ത്രത്തിന്റെ പിതാവായി കാണുന്നതാരെ? ",
    "answerText": " അരിസ്റ്റോട്ടിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83570,
    "questionText": " സാലിസ്ബറിയുടെ പുതിയ പേരെന്ത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഹരാരെ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83571,
    "questionText": " Which country has world’s largest cattle and buffalo population?",
    "answerText": " India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83572,
    "questionText": " കേരളത്തിൽ ദേശീയ ഗെയിംസ് നടത്തിയ വർഷം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": 1987
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83573,
    "questionText": " Sanjay Gandhi National Park is in?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83574,
    "questionText": " കേരളത്തിലെ ആദ്യ വനിതാ വൈസ് ചാൻസലർ ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോ. ജാൻസി ജെയിംസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83575,
    "questionText": " The hottest period all over India?",
    "answerText": " 3 p.m."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83576,
    "questionText": " To which religion Palitana is Gujarat is related?",
    "answerText": " Jainism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83577,
    "questionText": " കേരളത്തിലെ ഏറ്റവും വലിയ ശുദ്ധജലതടാകം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ശാസ്താംകോട്ട "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83578,
    "questionText": " കേരള തുളസിദാസൻ എന്ന് അറിയപ്പെടുന്ന കവി ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " വെണ്ണിക്കുളം ഗോപാലക്കുറുപ്പ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83579,
    "questionText": " What is the section of Indian Penal Code for bidding the assembly of more than 5 persons?",
    "answerText": 144
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83580,
    "questionText": " അരുണ രക്താണുക്കളുടെ ആയുർദൈർഘ്യം എത്ര ദിവസം ? ",
    "answerText": " 120 ദിവസം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83581,
    "questionText": " കോട്ടയം പട്ടണം ഏത് നദിയുടെ തീരത്താണ്? ",
    "answerText": " മീനച്ചിലാർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83582,
    "questionText": " സാധുജന പരിപാലന സംഘത്തിന്റെ സ്ഥാപകൻ ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " അയ്യങ്കാളി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83583,
    "questionText": " ഓമനത്തിങ്കൾകിടാവോ എന്ന താരാട്ടുപാട്ട് എഴുതിയത് ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഇരയിമ്മൻ തമ്പി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83584,
    "questionText": " ലോകത്തിലെ ആദ്യത്തെ വിദ്യാഭ്യാസ ഉപഗ്രഹം? ",
    "answerText": " എഡ്യുസാറ്റ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83585,
    "questionText": " Jog falls, the highest water fall in India, is situated in the river?",
    "answerText": " Sharavati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83586,
    "questionText": " അയർലൻഡിന്റെ തലസ്ഥാനം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡബ്ളിൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83587,
    "questionText": " ഗോൾഡൻ ഗേൾ എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നതാരെ? ",
    "answerText": " പി.ടി. ഉഷ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83588,
    "questionText": " ദത്തവകാശ നിരോധന നിയമം നടപ്പിലാക്കിയത് ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡൽഹൗസി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83589,
    "questionText": " പൂക്കൾക്കും ഇലകൾക്കും പർപ്പിൾ, നീല എന്നീ നിറങ്ങൾ നൽകുന്ന വർണകണം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " ആന്തോസിയാനിൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83590,
    "questionText": " സംസ്ഥാന മുഖ്യമന്ത്രി പദം അലങ്കരിച്ച ആദ്യത്തെ വനിത ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " സുചേതാ കൃപാലിനി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83591,
    "questionText": " മാമാങ്കം എത്ര വർഷത്തിലൊരിക്കലാണ് നടക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " 12 വർഷം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83592,
    "questionText": " ദക്ഷിണഗംഗ എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്ന നദി ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " കാവേരി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83593,
    "questionText": " The Danish East India Company was formed in 1616. ……… in Tamil Nadu coast was their main centre?",
    "answerText": " Tranquebar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83594,
    "questionText": " Antarctica Study centre in India is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83595,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യൻ ഭരണഘടനയിൽ എത്ര അദ്ധ്യായം ഉണ്ട്? ",
    "answerText": 22
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83596,
    "questionText": " തേയില കണ്ടുപിടിച്ചത് ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " ചൈനക്കാർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83597,
    "questionText": " The old name of ‘Rashtrapathi Bhavan’?",
    "answerText": " Viceregal palace"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83598,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state Asia’s first oil refinery was established?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83599,
    "questionText": " The place which is known as the “Mecca of temple architecture”?",
    "answerText": " Khajuraho"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83600,
    "questionText": " ഇന്ത്യയുടെ ആദ്യത്തെ രാഷ്ട്രപതി ആര്? ",
    "answerText": " ഡോ. രാജേന്ദ്രപ്രസാദ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83601,
    "questionText": " Longest tributary of Indus?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83602,
    "questionText": " ലോക മനുഷ്യാവകാശ ദിനം എന്ന് ? ",
    "answerText": " ഡിസംബർ 10 "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83603,
    "questionText": " Namdapha Tiger Reserve is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83604,
    "questionText": " ഏറ്റവും ഉയരമുള്ള അഗ്നിപർവതം ഏത്? ",
    "answerText": " കോട്ടോപാക്സി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83605,
    "questionText": " In Uttar Pradesh, the seat of High Court is?",
    "answerText": " Allahabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83606,
    "questionText": " Jatra is folk dance drama popular in the villages of?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83607,
    "questionText": " On which river is the Bhakra Nangal project built?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83608,
    "questionText": " Where one can see ‘Amar Jawan Jyothi’?",
    "answerText": " India Gate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83609,
    "questionText": " Garden Reach Shipbuilders and Engineers Ltd. is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83610,
    "questionText": " The oldest paramilitary force in India?",
    "answerText": " Assam Rifles"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83611,
    "questionText": " Kaiga Power Projet is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83612,
    "questionText": " Indian Cancer Research Centre is situated at?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83613,
    "questionText": " The most populated princely state in India at the time of independence?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83614,
    "questionText": " Sir Ronald Ross was born at?",
    "answerText": " Almora"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83615,
    "questionText": " The first state in South India where President’s rule was declared for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Andhra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83616,
    "questionText": " The largest non-capital city in South India?",
    "answerText": " Visakhapatnam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83617,
    "questionText": " The 8th city of Delhi?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83618,
    "questionText": " Saddle Peak which is the highest peak in Andaman and Nicobar group of islands. It is located in?",
    "answerText": " North Andaman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83619,
    "questionText": " The most famous monument in India?",
    "answerText": " Tajmahal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83620,
    "questionText": " The state in India with the largest percentage of rural population?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83621,
    "questionText": " Bibi-ka-Makbara is situated in?",
    "answerText": " Aurangabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83622,
    "questionText": " The Ganges beyond Farakka, after entering Bangladesh is known as?",
    "answerText": " Padma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83623,
    "questionText": " The Oldest rocks in India?",
    "answerText": " Aravallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83624,
    "questionText": " Ahmedabad is in the banks of?",
    "answerText": " Sabarmathi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83625,
    "questionText": " The Simhachalam Temple is dedicated to?",
    "answerText": " Narasimha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83626,
    "questionText": " To which religion ‘Tower of Silence’ is related?",
    "answerText": " Zorashtrians"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83627,
    "questionText": " Badrinath is on the banks of?",
    "answerText": " Alakananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83628,
    "questionText": " Uttaramerur inscription belongs to the period of?",
    "answerText": " Parantaka I"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83629,
    "questionText": " The most populous island in India?",
    "answerText": " Salsette"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83630,
    "questionText": " India’s first large scale steel plant in private sector was established at?",
    "answerText": " Jamshedpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83631,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of the North East Hill University (NEHU)?",
    "answerText": " Shillong"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83632,
    "questionText": " The battle which determined the fate of the French in India?",
    "answerText": " Wandiwash"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83633,
    "questionText": " The hill resort in Tamil Nadu where the Malayalee Temple is situated?",
    "answerText": " Yercaud"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83634,
    "questionText": " Who designed Mysore Palace?",
    "answerText": " Henry Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83635,
    "questionText": " Who designed Prince of Wales Museum in Mumbai?",
    "answerText": " George Wittet"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83636,
    "questionText": " The cities of Hyderabad and Secundarabad are seperated by?",
    "answerText": " Hussain Sagar lake"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83637,
    "questionText": " Dona Paula is a chief port in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83638,
    "questionText": " The district in Jammu and Kashmir 37,555 sq.km of which is under illegal occupation by China?",
    "answerText": " Ladakh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83639,
    "questionText": " The first state in India to implement Land reforms Bill and Education Reforms Bill?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83640,
    "questionText": " What is often called ‘Baby Taj’?",
    "answerText": " Mausoleum of Itmad-ud-Daulah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83641,
    "questionText": " India’s largest Mahayana Buddhist Monastery is Tawang Gompa. It is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83642,
    "questionText": " India’s first private air port was opened in 1999 in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83643,
    "questionText": " Chitharal Hills are in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83644,
    "questionText": " The first memorial of a sati, found at Eran, is dated 510 B.C. Eran is in?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83645,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state was Bhoodan Movement launched?",
    "answerText": " Pocahmapad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83646,
    "questionText": " India Gate is situated in?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83647,
    "questionText": " Which state is called theScotland of the East?",
    "answerText": " Shillong"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83648,
    "questionText": " Yakshagana is the dance form of?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83649,
    "questionText": " Which state is known as the ‘Kohinoor of India’?",
    "answerText": " Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83650,
    "questionText": " The first state in India to conduct elections to Panchayat Raj Institutions after the 73 rd amendment of the Constitution was brought into effect?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83651,
    "questionText": " What percentage of the world area is occupied by India?",
    "answerText": 2.4
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83652,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state is Vembanad Lake?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83653,
    "questionText": " With which country has India the longest border?",
    "answerText": " Bangladesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83654,
    "questionText": " The highest peak of western ghats or Sahyadri is Anaimudi. It is in?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83655,
    "questionText": " The meeting ground of eastern, western and southern ghats?",
    "answerText": " Nilgiri Hills"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83656,
    "questionText": " The highest peak of the Nilgiris?",
    "answerText": " Dodabetta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83657,
    "questionText": " The river which marks the international boundary between India and Nepal?",
    "answerText": " Gandak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83658,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest acrage of forest in India?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83659,
    "questionText": " Lunej Petrol producing area is located in?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83660,
    "questionText": " In India, the first unit of cement industry was established in 1904 at?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83661,
    "questionText": " The tribal population in Andaman and Nicobar islands belong to the?",
    "answerText": " Negroid race"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83662,
    "questionText": " National Remote Sensing Agency is located in?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83663,
    "questionText": " The world’s highest road connects?",
    "answerText": " LehManali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83664,
    "questionText": " The NH-44 is the longest national highway in India. It connects?",
    "answerText": " SrinagarKanyakumari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83665,
    "questionText": " Into how many pincode zones the country divided?",
    "answerText": 8
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83666,
    "questionText": " The earth station for satellite communication is located at?",
    "answerText": " Arvi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83667,
    "questionText": " The STD facility was first introduced in 1960 between?",
    "answerText": " Kanpur- Lucknow"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83668,
    "questionText": " Which is called the ‘Ruhr of India’?",
    "answerText": " Chotanagpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83669,
    "questionText": " The only anthrapoid ape found in India?",
    "answerText": " Hoolock Gibbon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83670,
    "questionText": " Which was the second district to achieve total literacy in India?",
    "answerText": " Dakshin Kannada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83671,
    "questionText": " The passage between South Andaman and Little Andaman?",
    "answerText": " Duncan Passage"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83672,
    "questionText": " Where is Gulf of Mannar located?",
    "answerText": " East of Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83673,
    "questionText": " When were the states of India organised on a linguistic basis?",
    "answerText": 1956
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83674,
    "questionText": " The highest peak in Indian territory including the disputed areas is K2. In which range it is located?",
    "answerText": " Karakoram Range"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83675,
    "questionText": " The total area covered by the Himalayas is about?",
    "answerText": " 500000 sq.km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83676,
    "questionText": " In which state are the Aravalli ranges located?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83677,
    "questionText": " Where is the Maikal range located?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83678,
    "questionText": " The territorial waters of India extend upto how many nautical miles?",
    "answerText": " Twelve"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83679,
    "questionText": " Which river in India is called Tsangpo in one of its reaches?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83680,
    "questionText": " In which area does the Sabarmati rise?",
    "answerText": " Aravallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83681,
    "questionText": " Which river flows between the Satpuras and the Vindhyas?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83682,
    "questionText": " When are temperatures the highest in Southern India?",
    "answerText": " April"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83683,
    "questionText": " Which is the southernmost unit of India?",
    "answerText": " Great Nicobar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83684,
    "questionText": " From which river has the Rajastan Canal (Indira Gandhi Canal) been taken out?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83685,
    "questionText": " Which area in India receives least rain fall?",
    "answerText": " Eastern Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83686,
    "questionText": " Which river has been harnessed under the Bhakra Nangal Project?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83687,
    "questionText": " In which state the Dhuvaran Thermal Power station is located?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83688,
    "questionText": " Where is Desert National Park situated?",
    "answerText": " Rajastan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83689,
    "questionText": " Khangchendzonga, one of the highest national parks in the world is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83690,
    "questionText": " Kodaikanal is situated in ......?",
    "answerText": " . Palani Hills"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83691,
    "questionText": " Which is the main religion in Ladakh?",
    "answerText": " Buddhism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83692,
    "questionText": " Which place is known as ‘Little Lhasa’?",
    "answerText": " Dharamsala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83693,
    "questionText": " Which is known as the Switzerland of Himachal Pradesh?",
    "answerText": " Khajjia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83694,
    "questionText": " Which is the native state of the tribe Gaddis?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83695,
    "questionText": " Indian Institute of Advanced Studies is in?",
    "answerText": " Shiml"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83696,
    "questionText": " Which was the summer capital of British India?",
    "answerText": " Shimla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83697,
    "questionText": " Where is the asylum of Dalai Lama?",
    "answerText": " Dharamsala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83698,
    "questionText": " Which is known as ‘All Seasons State’?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83699,
    "questionText": " In which state is the man made lake Govind Sagar?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83700,
    "questionText": " In which Indian state is Giri Hydel Project?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83701,
    "questionText": " In which state Kangra Valley, Lahul Valley are situated?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83702,
    "questionText": " Which state is called Fruit basket of India?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83703,
    "questionText": " Which state is called Apple state of India?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83704,
    "questionText": " Where is Central Potato Research Institute?",
    "answerText": " Shimla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83705,
    "questionText": " In which river is Nathpa Jhakri Project?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83706,
    "questionText": " The first state in India to ban plastic?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83707,
    "questionText": " Himachal Pradesh is the state where the polling for the first general election was started. It was in?",
    "answerText": 1951
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83708,
    "questionText": " India’s first carbon-free state?",
    "answerText": " Himachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83709,
    "questionText": " The main language of Himachal Pradesh?",
    "answerText": " Hindi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83710,
    "questionText": " The highest post office in the world?",
    "answerText": " Hikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83711,
    "questionText": " The highest state capital in India?",
    "answerText": " Shimla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83712,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest percentage of area under forest?",
    "answerText": " Mizoram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83713,
    "questionText": " Which State/Union Territory has the largest percentage of area under forest?",
    "answerText": " Andaman Nicobar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83714,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest mangrove forest area?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83715,
    "questionText": " Which state has the second largest mangrove forest area?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83716,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of the Forest Survey of India?",
    "answerText": " Dehra Dun"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83717,
    "questionText": " In which year Project Tiger was started?",
    "answerText": 1973
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83718,
    "questionText": " The minimum desired area which is considered safe for a tropical country like India?",
    "answerText": 33
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83719,
    "questionText": " Which state has the highest per capita forest area?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83720,
    "questionText": " Who started ‘Vana Maholsava’ in India?",
    "answerText": " KM Munshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83721,
    "questionText": " In which year ‘Vana Maholsava’was started?",
    "answerText": 1950
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83722,
    "questionText": " Nandan Canan in Orissa is famous for?",
    "answerText": " White Tiger"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83723,
    "questionText": " In which state is Trishna Sanctuary?",
    "answerText": " Tripura"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83724,
    "questionText": " Sanjay Gandhi National Park is adjacent to the city of?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83725,
    "questionText": " Guindy National Park is adjacent to the city of?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83726,
    "questionText": " The state which is also called ‘Vananchal’?",
    "answerText": " Jharkhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83727,
    "questionText": " The highest national park in India is situated in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83728,
    "questionText": " The largest mountain range in India?",
    "answerText": " Himalayas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83729,
    "questionText": " What is the length of Himalayas?",
    "answerText": " 2400 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83730,
    "questionText": " The correct order of mountain ranges in Himalayas from north to south?",
    "answerText": " Himadri; Himachal; Shiwalik"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83731,
    "questionText": " The founder of Arya Samaj?",
    "answerText": " Dayanand Saraswati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83732,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who followed ‘Forward Policy’?",
    "answerText": " Lord Lytton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83733,
    "questionText": " “Merely a mutiny of soldiers, which took the shape of revolt of people in certain areas” Who said this about the Mutiny of 1857?",
    "answerText": " Charles Raikes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83734,
    "questionText": " “The greatest son of India after Lord Buddha” who made this description about Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83735,
    "questionText": " “The Indian Rebellion of 1857 was not one movement …. it was many” – The above statement has been made by?",
    "answerText": " C.A. Bayly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83736,
    "questionText": " The permission to mint and issue coins in India was first given to the British East India Company in?",
    "answerText": 1685
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83737,
    "questionText": " The Peshwa who burnt the British residency at Pune?",
    "answerText": " Baji Rao II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83738,
    "questionText": " The place that was selected by Gandhiji to break salt law?",
    "answerText": " Dandi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83739,
    "questionText": " The place where the first war of independence was led by Kunwar Singh?",
    "answerText": " Jagdishpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83740,
    "questionText": " The policy of ‘Masterly Inactivity’ is associated with the name of the Governor General?",
    "answerText": " John Lawrence"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83741,
    "questionText": " The political guru of Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": " Gopala Krishna Gokhale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83742,
    "questionText": " The political guru of K.Kamaraj?",
    "answerText": " Satyamurti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83743,
    "questionText": " The Poona Pact (1932) upheld?",
    "answerText": " Joint electorate with reserved seats for the scheduled"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83744,
    "questionText": " The portfolio held by Dr.Rajendra Prasad in the interim government formed in 1946?",
    "answerText": " Food and Agriculture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83745,
    "questionText": " The Portugeuse East India Company was founded in?",
    "answerText": 1628
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83746,
    "questionText": " The position of the Peshwas became hereditary during the reign of?",
    "answerText": " Sahu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83747,
    "questionText": " The post of the Secretaty of State for India was created in?",
    "answerText": 1858
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83748,
    "questionText": " The president of the Swaraj Party was?",
    "answerText": " C.R.Das"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83749,
    "questionText": " The princely states that did not sign the Instrument of Accession by 15th August 1947 were Kashmir, Hyderabad and _____?",
    "answerText": " Junagarh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83750,
    "questionText": " The publication launched by Barindrakumar Ghosh and Bhupendernath Dutt in 1906?",
    "answerText": " Yugantar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83751,
    "questionText": " The publication launched by the British Committee of INC in 1890?",
    "answerText": " India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83752,
    "questionText": " The publication started by Gandhiji in 1933?",
    "answerText": " Harijan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83753,
    "questionText": " The publication started by Gandhiji in South Africa?",
    "answerText": " Indian Opinion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83754,
    "questionText": " The Quit India Day coincides with the anniversary of _____?",
    "answerText": " Kakori train robbery"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83755,
    "questionText": " “We do not ask favours, we only want justice”, these were the words of ______ ?",
    "answerText": " Dadabhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83756,
    "questionText": " “What began as a fight for religion, ended as a war of independence’: this remarks about the Revolt of 1857 was made by?",
    "answerText": " Dr.S.N.Sen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83757,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy during the Second Afghan War of (1878-80)?",
    "answerText": " Lytton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83758,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy during the Second and Third Round Table Conference?",
    "answerText": " Wellington"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83759,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy of British India who resigned over the question of Egypt?",
    "answerText": " Ripon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83760,
    "questionText": " Adayar was the famous centre and headquarters of the?",
    "answerText": " Theosophical Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83761,
    "questionText": " The venue of 1939 session of Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " Tripuri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83762,
    "questionText": " After independence, in which type of states former rulers were appointed as ‘Rajapramukh’ to head the administration?",
    "answerText": " Part B"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83763,
    "questionText": " After matriculation, in which college Gandhiji joined?",
    "answerText": " Samaldas College"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83764,
    "questionText": " After the Surat split of 1907, the second split of Indian National Congress took place in 1918 on the issue of?",
    "answerText": " Montague Declaration"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83765,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who appointed Hunter Commission to enquire into education?",
    "answerText": " Ripon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83766,
    "questionText": " After the withdrawl of non-cooperation movement, the Congress was divided into?",
    "answerText": " Pro-changers and no-changers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83767,
    "questionText": " Against what laws did Gandhiji along with other non-whites raise his voice in South Africa?",
    "answerText": " Apartheid laws"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83768,
    "questionText": " As per the resolution adpoted by the Committee of All Parties conference on 19th May 1928 who was made the chairman to consider and determine the principles of the Constitution of India?",
    "answerText": " Motilal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83769,
    "questionText": " Ashfaqulla Khan was sentenced to death in connection with?",
    "answerText": " Kakori Case"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83770,
    "questionText": " Asiatic Society of Bengal was established in?",
    "answerText": 1784
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83771,
    "questionText": " At the battle of Biddera the English crushed the power of ___?",
    "answerText": " Dutch"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83772,
    "questionText": " At the earlier stage backward classes movement means?",
    "answerText": " Non-Brahmin movement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83773,
    "questionText": " At the meeting held at ____ on 12th February 1922, the AICC decided to suspend non-cooperation movement in view of Chauri Chaura incidents?",
    "answerText": " Bardoli"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83774,
    "questionText": " At the time of independence the most populous princely state was?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83775,
    "questionText": " At what age did Gandhiji get married?",
    "answerText": " 13 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83776,
    "questionText": " At which Congress session was the Working Committee authorised to launch of programme of Civil Disobedience?",
    "answerText": " Lahore 1929"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83777,
    "questionText": " At which Gandhi Museum is the bloodstained dhoti preserved, which Gandhiji was wearing when he was shot dead?",
    "answerText": " Delhi Museum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83778,
    "questionText": " At whose advice Dayanand Saraswati changed his medium of speech to Hindi and started wearing regular clothes instead of remaining barebodied?",
    "answerText": " Keshab Chandra Sen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83779,
    "questionText": " Atmiya Sabha was founded in?",
    "answerText": 1815
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83780,
    "questionText": " Burma (Myanmar) was separated from India in?",
    "answerText": 1937
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83781,
    "questionText": " Burma was annexed to the British empire by a proclamation on 1st January, _____?",
    "answerText": 1855
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83782,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who announced the date of transfer of power to Indian hands?",
    "answerText": " Mountbatten"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83783,
    "questionText": " Disturbed by the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre and encouraged by Gandhiji’s plan for non-cooperation who resigned from ICS while on probation in 1921?",
    "answerText": " Subhas Chandra Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83784,
    "questionText": " Diu was the colony of the …………..?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83785,
    "questionText": " Division of the Civil Services into Imperial, Provincial and Subordinate was done during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Lord Lansdowne"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83786,
    "questionText": " Domingo Paes was a visitor from?",
    "answerText": " Portugal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83787,
    "questionText": " Dropping the use of the title ‘Emperor of India’ by the British Monarch was done by King George VI by a royal proclamation on?",
    "answerText": " 22 June 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83788,
    "questionText": " Due to which disease Gandhiji was compelled to leave England to India in 1914?",
    "answerText": " Pleurisy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83789,
    "questionText": " Durant Commission was appointed to demarcate the boundary betwen British India and Afgahnistan, during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Lansdowne"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83790,
    "questionText": " During which session of INC (1926) wearing Khadi was made compulsory to its workers?",
    "answerText": " Guwahati (1926)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83791,
    "questionText": " During 1940s,Nanasaheb Ramchandra Patil founded parallel government named Prati Sarkar in the 150 villages in?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83792,
    "questionText": " During Quit India movement, Tamralipta Jatiya Sarkar (Tamrlipta National Government) was formed in?",
    "answerText": " Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83793,
    "questionText": " During the freedom struggle ‘Anusheelan Samiti’ opened its branches in?",
    "answerText": " Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83794,
    "questionText": " During the Indian freedom struggle, why did Rowlatt Act arouse popular indignation?",
    "answerText": " It authorised the goverment to imprison people without trial"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83795,
    "questionText": " During the Quit India Movement a parallel government was setup by Nana Patil in ______ ?",
    "answerText": " Satara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83796,
    "questionText": " During the Quit India Movement the first ‘parallel government’ was established in?",
    "answerText": " Balia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83797,
    "questionText": " During the Quit India Movement what was formed in Tamluk?",
    "answerText": " Vidyut Vahini"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83798,
    "questionText": " During the Quit India Movement, Congress Radio was broadcast from?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83799,
    "questionText": " During the reign of which Viceroy of India elections were held for the first time in 11 Indian states in?",
    "answerText": " Lord Linlithgo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83800,
    "questionText": " During the revolt of 1857, Bahadur Shah was captured by the enemies from?",
    "answerText": " Humayun’s Tomb"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83801,
    "questionText": " During the revolt of 1857, Birjis Qadr, the son of the deposed Nawab Wajid Ali Shah, was proclaimed the new Nawab of?",
    "answerText": " Lucknow"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83802,
    "questionText": " During the revolt of 1857, Delhi was captured by the mutineers on?",
    "answerText": " 12th May 1857"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83803,
    "questionText": " During which agitation Gandhiji gave the slogan’ Do or die’?",
    "answerText": " Quit India movement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83804,
    "questionText": " During which occasion Gandhiji declared “Cooperation in any shape or form with this satanic government is sinful”?",
    "answerText": " Jallianwala Bagh Massacre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83805,
    "questionText": " During which period did Mahathma Gandhi emerge as a leader in India?",
    "answerText": " During the time of the Rowlatt Act"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83806,
    "questionText": " During which war Gandhi organised Indian Ambulance Corps to help the British?",
    "answerText": " Boer War"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83807,
    "questionText": " During whose era the Agra canal was finished?",
    "answerText": " British"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83808,
    "questionText": " During whose reign did the Marathas reach maximum expansion?",
    "answerText": " Balaji Baji Rao"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83809,
    "questionText": " During whose tenure as the Viceroy of India were the great martyrs Bhagat Singh, Sukhdev and Rajguru hanged?",
    "answerText": " Lord Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83810,
    "questionText": " During whose viceroyalty was the Railway Board set up?",
    "answerText": " Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83811,
    "questionText": " Editor of ‘Indu Prakash’ was?",
    "answerText": " Aurobindo Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83812,
    "questionText": " Congress Radio was the broadcasting mouthpiece of the Indian National Congress during Quit India Movement. Who organised it?",
    "answerText": " Usha Mehta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83813,
    "questionText": " Conquest and annexation of Sind (1843) was during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Lord Ellenborough"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83814,
    "questionText": " Cripp’s Mission visited India during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Linlithgo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83815,
    "questionText": " Cripp’s Mission visited India in?",
    "answerText": 1942
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83816,
    "questionText": " Curzon-Kitchner Controversy of 1904-05 is related to.........?",
    "answerText": " Abolition of military member in the Viceroy’s Council"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83817,
    "questionText": " Dadabhai Naoroji served as the prime minister of?",
    "answerText": " Baroda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83818,
    "questionText": " First Afghan War (1836-42) held during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Lord Auckland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83819,
    "questionText": " First Burmese War (1824-26) held during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Lord Amherst"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83820,
    "questionText": " From where Gandhiji passed matriculation?",
    "answerText": " Ahmedabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83821,
    "questionText": " From where was the Khilafat movement launched?",
    "answerText": " Karachi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83822,
    "questionText": " From which University in USA, B.R.Ambedkar received his Ph.D.?",
    "answerText": " Columbia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83823,
    "questionText": " From whom Gandhiji got the idea ‘Civil Disobedience’?",
    "answerText": " Henry David Thoreau"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83824,
    "questionText": " Gandhi ended his fast in Yervada prison which he started after the Communal Award of Ramsay Mc Donald, in consequent to?",
    "answerText": " Pune Pact"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83825,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji accorded very high priority to communal harmony in his programme of actions. At which place did he undertake his last fast for it on January 13, 1948?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83826,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji addressed Tagore as?",
    "answerText": " Gurudev"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83827,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji and General Smuts engaged in an agrrement in Pretoria in.... ?",
    "answerText": 1908
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83828,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji arrived India from South Africa in the year?",
    "answerText": 1915
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83829,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji believed that?",
    "answerText": " End and means both should be justified"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83830,
    "questionText": " First honorary president of All India Muslim League?",
    "answerText": " Aga Khan III"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83831,
    "questionText": " മനുഷ്യശരീരത്തിൽ ഏറ്റവും കുറവുള്ള മൂലകം? ",
    "answerText": " മാംഗനീസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83832,
    "questionText": " First joint session of Congress and Muslim League was held at Lucknow in?",
    "answerText": 1916
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83833,
    "questionText": " First Justice Party Government was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1920
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83834,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was assassinated in?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83835,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was assassinated on?",
    "answerText": " 30th January 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83836,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was born in a ...... Family?",
    "answerText": " Vaisya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83837,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji went to South Africa to appear in the court for the case of?",
    "answerText": " Sait Abdulla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83838,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji who was sentenced for six years imprisonment in 1922, was released in?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83839,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy when the Second World War was started?",
    "answerText": " Linlithgo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83840,
    "questionText": " ദ്രവ ഓക്‌സിജന്റെ നിറം? ",
    "answerText": " നേർത്ത നീല നിറം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83841,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji’s father passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1885
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83842,
    "questionText": " Gandhijji was undergone for imprisonment for ...... days in his whole life?",
    "answerText": 2338
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83843,
    "questionText": " ‘Generations to come, it may scarce to believe that such a one as him ever walked on this earth in flesh and blood”, who made this statement?",
    "answerText": " Albert Einstein"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83844,
    "questionText": " Godse, the assassin of Gandhiji, was the editor of?",
    "answerText": " Hindu Rashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83845,
    "questionText": " Gomdhar Kunwar was the leader of which movement?",
    "answerText": " Ahom Movement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83846,
    "questionText": " Gopala Krishna Gokhale passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1915
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83847,
    "questionText": " Government of India Act of 1935 was introduced when .... was the Viceroy?",
    "answerText": " Wellington"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83848,
    "questionText": " ‘Hamdard’ was started by?",
    "answerText": " Muhammad Ali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83849,
    "questionText": " He was a capitalist and served as the treasurer of AICC for many years and went in jail in 1930. Who was he?",
    "answerText": " Jamnalal Bajaj"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83850,
    "questionText": " He was born with a withered arm and no left hand. He was appointed Viceroy of India in 1926. Name this person?",
    "answerText": " Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83851,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji founded the Sabarmati Ashram in?",
    "answerText": 1915
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83852,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji got Barrister at Law from?",
    "answerText": " England"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83853,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji got primary education in?",
    "answerText": " Rajkot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83854,
    "questionText": " How many days did it take to complete the process of transfer of power from the British to India as per the Mountbatten plan?",
    "answerText": 72
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83855,
    "questionText": " How many fasts were undertaken by Gandhiji throughout his life?",
    "answerText": 30
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83856,
    "questionText": " How many Home Rule Leagues were formed in India in 1916?",
    "answerText": 2
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83857,
    "questionText": " How many members from Muslim League joined the interim government in October 1946?",
    "answerText": 5
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83858,
    "questionText": " How many members of the British Parliament were included in the Board of Control formed as per the Pitt’s India Act, 1784?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83859,
    "questionText": " How many Oscar Awards were received by the film ‘Gandhi’?",
    "answerText": 8
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83860,
    "questionText": " How many times did Gandhiji’s father married?",
    "answerText": " Four"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83861,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who headed the interim government assumed office on 2nd September, 1946?",
    "answerText": " Wavell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83862,
    "questionText": " വംശനാശഭീഷണി നേരിടുന്ന ജീവജാലങ്ങളെ അവയുടെ ആവാസകേന്ദ്രങ്ങളിൽ തന്നെ സംരക്ഷിക്കാൻ ശ്രമിക്കുന്ന പ്രകൃതി സംരക്ഷണ സംഘടന? ",
    "answerText": " WWF"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83863,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who inaugurated a new province known as the North West Frontier?",
    "answerText": " Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83864,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who introduced Budget system in India?",
    "answerText": " Canning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83865,
    "questionText": " “Long years ago we made a tryst with destiny, and now the time comes when we shall redeem our pledge, not wholly or in full measure, but very substantially. At the stroke of the midnight hour, when the world sleeps, India will awake to life and freedom.” Whose words are these?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83866,
    "questionText": " IUCN ന്റെ പൂർണ പേര്? ",
    "answerText": " International Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83867,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who created North West Frontier Province in 1901 directly under the Government of India?",
    "answerText": " Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83868,
    "questionText": " WHO രൂപം കൊണ്ടത്? ",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83869,
    "questionText": " The viceroy who earned the nick name ‘Clemency’?",
    "answerText": " Canning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83870,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who faced the Famine of 1943?",
    "answerText": " Wavell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83871,
    "questionText": " ടാക്സോണമിയുടെ പിതാവ്? ",
    "answerText": " കാൾ ലിനേയസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83872,
    "questionText": " How many times was Gandhiji arrested in South Africa during the Satyagraha?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83873,
    "questionText": " ജീവികൾക്കു പേരിടാനുള്ള ശ്രമങ്ങൾക്ക് തുടക്കമിട്ടത്? ",
    "answerText": " കാൾലിനേയസ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83874,
    "questionText": " 2004ൽ IUPAC വില്യം റോൺജന്റെ സ്മരണാർത്ഥം 111-ാമത്തെ മൂലകത്തിന് നാമകരണം ചെയ്തത് ? ",
    "answerText": " റോൺജനീയം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83875,
    "questionText": " Hughly was used as a base for piracy in the Bay of Bengal by the?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83876,
    "questionText": " Ibrabim Rugova, who is known as ‘Balkan Gandhi’ led the national movement in?",
    "answerText": " Kosovo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83877,
    "questionText": " Identify the Governor General who introduced the policy of auctioning the rights of revenue collection to the highest bidders?",
    "answerText": " Warren Hastings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83878,
    "questionText": " ഭൂമിയിൽ ജീവനടിസ്ഥാനമായ മൂലകം? ",
    "answerText": " കാർബൺ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83879,
    "questionText": " ജലം ഹൈഡ്രജന്റെയും ഓക്സിജന്റെയും സംയുക്തമാണെന്ന് ആദ്യമായി തെളിയിച്ചത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഹെന്റി കാവൻഡിഷ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83880,
    "questionText": " Identify the leader who last met Gandhiji for about an hour and left him just few minutes before he was shot dead on January 30, 1948 while on his way to the prayer meeting?",
    "answerText": " Sardar Patel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83881,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was born on?",
    "answerText": " 2nd October 1869"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83882,
    "questionText": " വൈദ്യുതി കടത്തിവിടാത്ത കാർബണിന്റെ രൂപാന്തരമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " വജ്രം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83883,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was imprisoned for ...... days in India?",
    "answerText": 2089
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83884,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was imprisoned for the first time in?",
    "answerText": " Johannesberg"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83885,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was sentenced for six years imprisonment in 1922 for sedition on behalf of the articles published in?",
    "answerText": " Young India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83886,
    "questionText": " Gandhiji was the first Indian to become a lawyer in Natal High Court. In which year did Gandhiji become a lawyer there?",
    "answerText": 1894
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83887,
    "questionText": " ജ്വലനത്തെ അണയ്ക്കാൻ സഹായിക്കുന്ന വാതകം? ",
    "answerText": " കാർബൺ ഡൈ ഓക്സൈഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83888,
    "questionText": " Identify the main centre of the Revolt of 1857 which was first recaptured by the British?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83889,
    "questionText": " അരുണ രക്താണുക്കൾ അരിവാളിന്റെ ആകൃതിയിൽ വരുന്ന രോഗമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " സിക്കിൾ സെൽ അനീമിയ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83890,
    "questionText": " Identify the Viceroy who wrote home these words after his first meeting with Gandhiji, “Mr Gandhi’s religious and moral views are, I believe, admirable, but I confess that I find it difficult to understand the practice of them in politics.”",
    "answerText": " Lord Reading"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83891,
    "questionText": " അരുണ രക്താണുക്കളുടെ ശവപ്പറമ്പ് എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്ന അവയവം? ",
    "answerText": " പ്ളീഹ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83892,
    "questionText": " മനുഷ്യശരീരത്തിലെ ബ്ളഡ് ബാങ്ക്? ",
    "answerText": " പ്ളീഹ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83893,
    "questionText": " മർമം ഇല്ലാത്ത രക്തകോശങ്ങൾ? ",
    "answerText": " അരുണ രക്താണുക്കൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83894,
    "questionText": " In 1650 Gabriel Boughton, an employee of the Company obtained a license for trade in ………….?",
    "answerText": " Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83895,
    "questionText": " ശരീരത്തിലെ പട്ടാളക്കാർ എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്ന ശ്വേതരക്താണു? ",
    "answerText": " ന്യൂട്രോഫിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83896,
    "questionText": " ശ്വേതരക്താണുവിന്റെ ശാസ്ത്രീയനാമം? ",
    "answerText": " ലൂക്കോസൈറ്റ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83897,
    "questionText": " WBCയുടെ ആയുസ്? ",
    "answerText": " 10 - 15 ദിവസം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83898,
    "questionText": " In 1765, the British managed to get the Diwani rights of?",
    "answerText": " Bengal; Orissa; Bihar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83899,
    "questionText": " പ്ളാസ്മയുടെ നിറം? ",
    "answerText": " വൈക്കോലിന്റെ നിറം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83900,
    "questionText": " അടിച്ചുപരത്തി തകിടുകളാക്കാൻ പറ്റുന്ന ലോഹങ്ങളുടെ കഴിവ്? ",
    "answerText": " മാലിയബിലിറ്റി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83901,
    "questionText": " In 1877 the entrance age to ICS was reduced from 21 to ……?",
    "answerText": 19
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83902,
    "questionText": " In 1878, the government reduced the maximum age limit for the open competition for the civil service examination from 21 to?",
    "answerText": 19
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83903,
    "questionText": " വൈദ്യുത പ്രവാഹത്തെ ഒരേ ദിശയിൽ മാത്രം ആക്കുന്ന പ്രവർത്തനം? ",
    "answerText": " റെക്ടിഫിക്കേഷൻ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83904,
    "questionText": " വൈദ്യുതചാർജ് അല്പസമയം സംഭരിച്ചുവയ്ക്കാൻ ഉപയോഗിക്കുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " കപ്പാസിറ്ററുകൾ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83905,
    "questionText": " In 1885 Dadabhai Naoroji was elected one of the vice presidents of?",
    "answerText": " Bombay Presidency Association"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83906,
    "questionText": " ശൂന്യതയിൽ പ്രകാശം സെക്കൻഡിൽ എത്ര കിലോമീറ്റർ സഞ്ചരിക്കുന്നു? ",
    "answerText": " 3 ലക്ഷം കിലോമീറ്റർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83907,
    "questionText": " തീരത്തുനിന്ന് 24 നോട്ടിക്കൽ മൈൽ വരെയുള്ള സമുദ്രഭാഗമാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " കണ്ടിജൻസ് സോൺ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83908,
    "questionText": " മത്സ്യബന്ധനം, എണ്ണപര്യവേക്ഷണം എന്നിവയ്ക്കെല്ലാം രാജ്യത്തിന് അവകാശമുള്ള സോണാണ് ? ",
    "answerText": " എക്സ്‌ക്ളൂസീവ് എക്കണോമിക് സോൺ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83909,
    "questionText": " In 1914 Gandhiji ended his stay in South Africa and went to?",
    "answerText": " London"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83910,
    "questionText": " 2014ലെ 20 - 20 ലോകകപ്പ് വേദി? ",
    "answerText": " ബംഗ്ളാദേശ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83911,
    "questionText": " ആദ്യ 20 - 20 ലോകകപ്പ് നേടിയ ഇന്ത്യൻ നായകൻ? ",
    "answerText": " എം.എസ്. ധോണി "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83912,
    "questionText": " ചരിത്രത്തിലെ ആദ്യ ടെസ്റ്റ് മത്സരവും ഏകദിന മത്സരവും നടന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " ഇംഗ്ളണ്ടും ആസ്ട്രേലിയയും തമ്മിൽ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83913,
    "questionText": " In the Ahmedabad Mill Strike, Mahathma Gandhi’s intervention resulted in the enhancement of wages of workers by?",
    "answerText": 0.35
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83914,
    "questionText": " In the Federation established by the Act 1935, residuary powers were given to the?",
    "answerText": " Governor General"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83915,
    "questionText": " In the Indian National Congress, the period between 1885 and 1905 came to be known as?",
    "answerText": " Moderate phase"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83916,
    "questionText": " In the last months of Gandhiji’s life, he fasted to end bloody clashes between Muslims and Hindus in which two cities?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata and Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83917,
    "questionText": " In the regime of which Governor General did the most number of native states were annexed to the British Empire?",
    "answerText": " Lord Dalhousie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83918,
    "questionText": " In the tenure of which Governor General an attempt was made for the first time to codify Hindu and Muslim customery laws?",
    "answerText": " Warren Hastings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83919,
    "questionText": " In the Third Maratha War, the English defeated Peshwa Bajirao II at—?",
    "answerText": " Bassein"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83920,
    "questionText": " In which city Tipu Sultan planted ‘Tree of Liberty’?",
    "answerText": " Srirangapatnam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83921,
    "questionText": " In which country “The Indian War of Independence’ authored by V.D.Savarkar was published for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Netherlands"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83922,
    "questionText": " In which language Gandhiji started the weekly ‘Young India’?",
    "answerText": " English"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83923,
    "questionText": " In which year the assassins of Gandhiji was executed?",
    "answerText": 1949
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83924,
    "questionText": " In which year the British Prime Minister Ramsay Mc Donald announced Communal Award?",
    "answerText": 1932
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83925,
    "questionText": " In which year the Congress ministries in the provinces resigned to protest against the war policy of the British Government?",
    "answerText": 1939
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83926,
    "questionText": " In which year the film ‘Gandhi’ got 8 Oscar Awards?",
    "answerText": 1982
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83927,
    "questionText": " In which year the first issue of Young India was published under the editorialship of Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": 1919
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83928,
    "questionText": " The book written by Gandhiji in 1909 during his sail for London?",
    "answerText": " Hind Swaraj"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83929,
    "questionText": " The booklets like “Loyal Muhammadans of India” and “Cause of Indian Revolt” were written by?",
    "answerText": " Syed Ahmed Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83930,
    "questionText": " The British Committee of Indian National Congress was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1889
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83931,
    "questionText": " The British got Kohinoor from?",
    "answerText": " Dalip Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83932,
    "questionText": " The British introduced the railways in India in order to?",
    "answerText": " facilitate British commerce and administrative control"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83933,
    "questionText": " The British king whom Gandhiji visited when he reached London for the Round Table Conference?",
    "answerText": " George V"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83934,
    "questionText": " The British officer who under his own authority shot Bahadur Shah Zafar’s sons Mirza Mughal, Mirza Khazir Sultan, and grandson Mirza Abu Bakr at the Khooni Darwaza?",
    "answerText": " William Hodson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83935,
    "questionText": " In which year the first meeting of AITUC was held?",
    "answerText": 1920
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83936,
    "questionText": " In which year the first Round Table Conference was held in London?",
    "answerText": 1930
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83937,
    "questionText": " In which year the first son of Gandhiji was born?",
    "answerText": 1888
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83938,
    "questionText": " India became a member of United nations in?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83939,
    "questionText": " India Councils Act of 1861 was passed during the tenure of?",
    "answerText": " Canning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83940,
    "questionText": " Indian Association wasestablished by Ananda Mohan Bose and ........in 1876?",
    "answerText": " Surendranath Bannerjee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83941,
    "questionText": " Julius Nyerere, the first to get Gandhi Peace Prize, led the national movement in?",
    "answerText": " Tanzania"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83942,
    "questionText": " Jyotiba Phule was one of the prominent ………….of the 19th century India?",
    "answerText": " Social reformers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83943,
    "questionText": " Kachnagas revolt took place in?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83944,
    "questionText": " Kanpur Conference, which is regarded as the foundation of the Communist Party of India in 1925, was held under the presidency of?",
    "answerText": " Singaravelu Chettiar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83945,
    "questionText": " ‘Karm Yogi’ was started by?",
    "answerText": " Aurobindo Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83946,
    "questionText": " Kheda where Gandhiji conducted Satyagraha is in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83947,
    "questionText": " Khilafat movement was originally a?",
    "answerText": " Religious movement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83948,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy when the First Round Table Conference was held in 1930?",
    "answerText": " Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83949,
    "questionText": " Lakshminath Bezbarua was a nationalist writer in___ during the freedom movement?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83950,
    "questionText": " Madras Mahajana Sabha was established by S.Ramaswami Mudaliyar and ______ in 1884?",
    "answerText": " P.Ananda Charlu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83951,
    "questionText": " Madras Mahajana Sabha was established in?",
    "answerText": 1884
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83952,
    "questionText": " Mahadji, the famous Maratha ruler of the later half of 18th century, belonged to the house of?",
    "answerText": " Sindhia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83953,
    "questionText": " Mahe was a colony of …………..?",
    "answerText": " French"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83954,
    "questionText": " Mangal Pandey was hanged on?",
    "answerText": " 1857 March 29"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83955,
    "questionText": " Mangal Pandey, the first martyr of 1857 revolt was a member of _____?",
    "answerText": " 34th Native Infantry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83956,
    "questionText": " Members of the Constituent Assembly appended their signatures on the Constitution on?",
    "answerText": " 24th January 1950"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83957,
    "questionText": " In which year the Swaraj Party founded by CR Das and Motilal Nehru started functioning?",
    "answerText": 1923
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83958,
    "questionText": " In which year was Kheda satyagraha of Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": 1918
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83959,
    "questionText": " Mountbatten stepped down from the position of Governor General of Independent India in?",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83960,
    "questionText": " Mrs.Annie Besant set up Home Rule League in September 1916 with its seat at?",
    "answerText": " Adayar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83961,
    "questionText": " Muhammad Ali Jinnah, the political rival of Mahathma Gandhi, passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83962,
    "questionText": " Mulsim League observed ‘Direct Action Day’ in?",
    "answerText": 1946
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83963,
    "questionText": " Muslim Leage joined the Interim Government on?",
    "answerText": " 26th October 1946"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83964,
    "questionText": " Netaji founded Forward Bloc in?",
    "answerText": 1940
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83965,
    "questionText": " Netaji Subhas Bose founded Azad Hind Government at Singapore in?",
    "answerText": 1943
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83966,
    "questionText": " In which language Gandhiji wrote Hind Swaraj?",
    "answerText": " Gujarati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83967,
    "questionText": " In which language Raja Ram Mohun Roy published his journal “Mirat-ul-Akhbar”?",
    "answerText": " Persian"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83968,
    "questionText": " In which year Lahore session of Indian National Congress declared that its was complete independence?",
    "answerText": 1929
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83969,
    "questionText": " In which year Mahadev Desai, the private secretary of Gandhiji passed away?",
    "answerText": 1944
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83970,
    "questionText": " In which year non-cooperation movement was suspended after Chauri-Chaura incident?",
    "answerText": 1922
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83971,
    "questionText": " In which year Numismatic Society of India was established at Allahabad?",
    "answerText": 1910
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83972,
    "questionText": " In which year Rowlatt Bill introduced?",
    "answerText": 1919
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83973,
    "questionText": " In which year Sarojini Naidu became the first Indian woman to become the president of Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": 1925
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83974,
    "questionText": " In which year split in All India Trade Union Congress took place?",
    "answerText": 1929
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83975,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy when the First World War was started?",
    "answerText": " Hardinge II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83976,
    "questionText": " In which year the administration of British India was transferred from East India Company to British Crown?",
    "answerText": 1858
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83977,
    "questionText": " Netaji Subhas Bose passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83978,
    "questionText": " Netaji Subhas Chandra Bose established provisional government of India (Government of Azad Hind ) based in Singapore on?",
    "answerText": " 21st October 1942"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83979,
    "questionText": " Nirankari Movement was started by?",
    "answerText": " Dayal Das"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83980,
    "questionText": " Number of Princely states at the time of independence?",
    "answerText": 562
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83981,
    "questionText": " Number of woman attended the first session of the Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " No woman attended"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83982,
    "questionText": " On 12th November 1930 who officially opened the Round Table Conference?",
    "answerText": " George V"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83983,
    "questionText": " On 9th of August, 1942, Mahatma Gandhi and the entire Congress Working Committee were arrested in _____ ?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83984,
    "questionText": " Muslim League observed 23rd March 1943 as?",
    "answerText": " Pakistan Day"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83985,
    "questionText": " Muslim League was formed at?",
    "answerText": " Dacca"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83986,
    "questionText": " ‘My one man army’ who made this remark about Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": " Lord Mountbatten"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83987,
    "questionText": " Namdhari Movement, populary called Kuka Movement was launched by?",
    "answerText": " Balak Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83988,
    "questionText": " Name a newspaper that was instrumental in inculcating the spirit of opposition to the Partition of Bengal?",
    "answerText": " Sandhya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83989,
    "questionText": " Name my eldest brother?",
    "answerText": " Lakshmidas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83990,
    "questionText": " Name the British Prime Minister when the Revolt of 1857 was started?",
    "answerText": " Palmerstone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83991,
    "questionText": " Name the freedom fighter who passed away on August 15, 1947?",
    "answerText": " Ajith Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83992,
    "questionText": " On what basis Pradesh Congress Committee was created?",
    "answerText": " Language"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83993,
    "questionText": " Pondicherry was the main base on the coromandel coast of the?",
    "answerText": " French East India Company"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83994,
    "questionText": " Poona Pact aimed at?",
    "answerText": " Representation of the lower classes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83995,
    "questionText": " Ram Prasad Bismil was hanged in association with....... Conspiracy Case?",
    "answerText": " Kakori"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83996,
    "questionText": " Ramakrishna Mission was founded by Vivekananda in?",
    "answerText": 1897
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83997,
    "questionText": " On what charges was Gandhiji arrested in 1922?",
    "answerText": " Sedition"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83998,
    "questionText": " On which date Gandhij was arrested in connection with Civil Disobedience Movement?",
    "answerText": " 5th May 1930"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 83999,
    "questionText": " Out of the total of 562 Princely States in undivided India, how many of them were within the new Independent India?",
    "answerText": 532
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 84000,
    "questionText": " Pacific Coast Hindustan Association was called?",
    "answerText": " Ghadar Party"
  }
]